（翻译：Allen, Adam）
（https://github.com/ivanallen/thor）
好啦，咱们开始上课
all right well let's get started
今天和明天我们打算讲讲 RAFT
today and indeed today and tomorrow I'm
gonna talk about raft both because I
希望这对你后面实现 labs 有所帮助
hope it'll be helpful you for you in
implementing though the labs and also
咱们会详尽的讨论实现正确的“复制状态机”的相关细节
because you know it's just a case study
in the details of how to get state
咱们会详尽的讨论实现正确的“复制状态机”的相关细节
machine replication correct so we have
这些问题之前我们都已经介绍过
introduction to the problem you may have
你可能已经注意到目前为止所有介绍过的容错系统中的模式
noticed a pattern in fault-tolerant
systems that we've looked at so far
其中之一就是 MapReduce 里的复制方案
one is that MapReduce replicates
但是它的整个复制完全由单个 master 所控制
computation but the replication is
controlled the whole computation is
但是它的整个复制完全由单个 master 所控制
controlled by a single master
另一个值得注意的例子是关于 GFS 复制数据
another example I'd like to draw your attention
to is that GFS replicates data right as
它通过 primary backup(主备) 方案复制实际文件内容
this primary backup scheme for
replicating the actual contents of files
但这个方案依赖于单一的 master 节点为每一片数据选择 primary
but it relies on a single master to
choose who the primary is for every
另一个是 vmware ft 复制方案
piece of data another example vmware ft
它在一台 primary 虚拟机和 backup 虚拟机上执行写入
replicates computational write on a
primary virtual machine and a backup
如果它们之一出故障 就需要搞清楚下一步该怎么做
virtual machine but in order to figure
out what to do next if one of them seems
这需要借助 test-and-set 服务器来帮助它选择一台 backup 来接管 primary
to a fail it relies on a single test and
set server to help the choose to help it
这需要借助 test-and-set 服务器来帮助它选择一台 backup 来接管 primary
ensure that exactly one of the primary
of the backup takes over if there's some kind of failure
这三个案例都有一个复制系统
so in all three of these
cases sure there was a replication
它们的复制系统隐藏的比较深
system but sort of tucked away in a
corner in the replication system there
它们都有一个相同的模式
was some scheme where a single entity
即需要一个单一的“实体”来判定谁是 primary
was required to make a critical decision
即需要一个单一的 entity (实体)来判定谁是 primary
about who the primary was in the cases we care about
单一实体的好处是它能决定谁来当 primary，它不能否定它自己
having a single entity decide who's
gonna be the primary is that it can't
单一实体的好处是它能决定谁来当 primary，它不能否定它自己
disagree with itself right there's only
只有它才能做出这个决策
one of it makes some decision that's the
但是这也导致一些缺点，比如会出现单点故障
decision it made but the bad thing about
having a single entity decide like who
但是这也导致一些缺点，比如会出现单点故障
the primary is is that it itself as a
single point of failure and so you can
所以你会发现这些系统它把 FT 的真正的核心机制放在一个角落里
view these systems that we've looked at
it sort of pushing the real heart of the
所以你会发现这些系统它把 FT 的真正的核心机制放在一个角落里
fault tolerance
Machinery into a little corner that is
即如果发生故障，用单一实体来决策谁是 primary
the single entity that decides who's
going to be the primary if there's a
他们这么做的目的就是为了防止 split brain(脑裂)
failure now this whole thing is about
how to avoid split brain the reason why
如果系统发生故障，需要非常小心的去决策谁是 primary
we have to have have to be extremely
careful about making the decision about
如果系统发生故障，需要非常小心的去决策谁是 primary
who should be the primary if there's a
否则就会有 split brain 的风险
failure is that otherwise we risks split
为了让这个问题变清晰
brain and just make this point super
我打算提醒你一下，这是个什么样的问题，为什么这个问题很严重
clear I'm gonna just remind you what the
problem is and why it's a serious
假设我们想构建一个有复制功能的 test-and-set 服务器
problem so supposing for example where
we want to build ourselves a replicated
假设我们想构建一个有复制功能的 test-and-set 服务器
test and set server that is we're
我们比较担心的是 vmware ft 依赖于这个 test-and-set 服务器去选择谁是 primary,
worried about the fact that vmware ft
我们比较担心的是 vmware ft 依赖于这个 test-and-set 服务器去选择谁是 primary
relies on this test and set server to
让我们构建一个有复制能力的 test-and-set 服务器
choose who the primary is so let's build
a replicated test and set server i'm
然后看看它发生故障后会是什么样子
gonna do this it's gonna be broken it's
我只是想解释一下为什么解决脑裂的问题很难
just an illustration for why why it's
difficult to get split brain problem
我只是想解释一下为什么解决脑裂的问题很难
correctly so you know we're gonna
想象一下我们有一个这样的网络
imagine we have a network and maybe two
然后这里有 2 台服务器，假设他们就是 test-and-set 服务的副本
servers which are supposed to be
replicas of our test and set service
这里有 2 个客户端，它们需要知道谁是 primary
connected and you know maybe two clients
they need to know who's the primary
事实上在这个例子里 client 就是前面课中讲的 vmware ft 中的 primary 和 backup
right now or actually maybe these
clients in this case are the primary in
事实上在这个例子里 client 就是前面课中讲的 vmware ft 中的 primary 和 backup
the back up in vmware ft so if it's a
如果这里是 test-and-set 服务器
test and set service then you know both
然后这里 2 个数据库会以它们自己的状态开始启动
these databases mostly servers start out
with their state that is the state of
刚开始他们的值都是 0
this test-and-set in zero and the
客户端的通过发送 test-and-set 指令把副本的 flag 设置成 1
one operation their clients can send is
the test and set operation which is
客户端的通过发送 test-and-set 指令把副本的 flag 设置成 1
supposed to set the flag of the
replicated service to one so i should
我应该要对这 2 个副本都进行设置，然后返回它的旧值
set both copies and then return the old
所以它看起来特别像一个简单版的 lock server
value so it's essentially acts as a kind
of simplified lock server okay so the
当有一个 client 只能与这 2 台 server 之一通信，而不能与另一台通信
我们所担心的脑裂就会发生
problem situation the lowly worried
当有一个 client 只能与这 2 台 server 之一通信，而不能与另一台通信
我们所担心的脑裂就会发生
about split-brain arises when a client
当有一个 client 只能与这 2 台 server 之一通信，而不能与另一台通信
我们所担心的脑裂就会发生
can talk to one of the servers but can't
当有一个 client 只能与这 2 台 server 之一通信，而不能与另一台通信
我们所担心的脑裂就会发生
talk to the other so we're imagining
来想象一下，当客户端发送请求给这 2 个服务器
either that when client send a request
they send it to both I'm just gonna
我只是假设哈，这一点也不重要
assume that now and almost doesn't
假设客户端发送任意的请求到这 2 个服务器
matter so let's assume that the protocol
is that the client supposed to send
假设客户端发送任意的请求到这 2 个服务器
ordinarily any request to both servers
如果其中 1 个服务器不响应，思考一下，客户端该怎么做？
and somehow we you know we need
think through what the client should do
如果其中 1 个服务器不响应，思考一下，客户端该怎么做？
if one of the server's doesn't respond
或者说系统应该怎么做？
right or what the system should do if
one of the servers doesn't respond
好，来想象一下，假设 C1 可以与 S1 通信，但不能与 S2 通信
so let's imagine now the
client one can contact server one but
好，来想象一下，假设 C1 可以与 S1 通信，但不能与 S2 通信
not server two how should the system
系统应该要怎么响应？
react one possibility is for is that we
我们当然不想让 C1 只能和 S1 通信
think well you know gosh we certainly
don't want to just talk to client to
我们当然不想让 C1 只能和 S1 通信
server one because that would leave the
如果我们只把这里设置成 1，而没有把另一台设置成 1
就会导致 S1 和 S2 数据不一致
second replica inconsistent if we set
如果我们只把这里设置成 1，而没有把另一台设置成 1
就会导致 S1 和 S2 数据不一致
this value to one but didn't also set
如果我们只把这里设置成 1，而没有把另一台设置成 1
就会导致 S1 和 S2 数据不一致
this value to one
正确的规则是，对任何要发送的指令，客户端必须总是能和这 2 台副本进行通信
so maybe the rule should be that the
client is always required to talk to
正确的规则是，对任何要发送的指令，客户端必须总是能和这 2 台副本进行通信
both replicas to both servers for any
只能和其中之一通信这是不允许的
operation and shouldn't be allowed to
just talk to one of them so why is that
为什么这会导致错误的结果？
the wrong answer so the rule is o in our
在这个复制系统中，客户端必须总是能和所有副本通信，以便后续步骤能正常进行
replicated system the clients always
require to talk to both replicas in
在这个复制系统中，客户端必须总是能和所有副本通信，以便后续步骤能正常进行
order to make progress
这并不是一个容错系统，事实上这会让事情更加糟糕
it's not fault tolerant at all in fact it's worse it's worse than talking to a
这比你和单个服务器通信还要糟糕
single server because now the system has
因为现在系统如果有问题，其中之一宕机了
a problem if either of these servers is
你就不能无法和它通信了
crashed or or you can't talk to it at
至少在只有一台服务的非复制系统中，你仅仅只依赖一台 server
least with a non replicated service
you're only depending on one server but
但现在，我们却要求这 2 台服务器都要在线
here we am both servers have to be alive
如果我们要求客户端同时和 2 台服务器通信
if we require the client to talk to both
那么所有服务器都必须在线
servers then both servers has to be alive
事实上，我们不能要求客户端去等待所有的服务器的响应
否则这就无法容错了
so we can't possibly require the client
事实上，我们不能要求客户端去等待所有的服务器的响应
否则这就无法容错了
to actually you know wait for both
事实上，我们不能要求客户端去等待所有的服务器的响应
否则这就无法容错了
servers to respond if we don't have
所以我们要能去处理这种问题
fault tolerance we need it to be able to
一个显而易见的答案是如果客户端不能和所有服务器通信
proceed so another obvious answer is
that if the client can't talk to both
那就让它能和那个可以通信的服务器通信就行了
well it just talks to the one who can
并且还能告诉你另一台服务器已经挂了
talk to and figures the other ones dead
但是这样做不对，为什么？
so what's up why is that also not the
right answer
麻烦的是如果另一台服务器它并没有宕机
the troubling scenario is if the other
server is actually alive so suppose the
假设这台服务器没有宕机，看起来似乎挺好的
actual problem or encountering is not
that this server crashed which would be
但糟糕的是这里的网线出了点问题
good for us but the much worse issue
that something went wrong with the
但糟糕的是这里的网线出了点问题
network cable and that this client can
C1 可以和 S1 通信但不能和 S2 通信
talk to client one can talk to server one
but not server two and there's maybe
而另一个客户端 C2 可以和 S2 通信但是不能与 S1 通信
some other client out there that conduct
a server two but not server one so if we
如果我们制定这样的规则：如果客户端能和所有服务通信
make the rule that if a client can talk
to both servers that it's okay in order
为了能够容错，我只要和其中之一通信就 okay
to be fault tolerant that I just talked
然后就会不可避免的发生一些事情，比如这里的网线断了
to one then what's just inevitably gonna
happen said this cable is gonna break
然后就会不可避免的发生一些事情，比如这里的网线断了
thus cutting the network in half client
C1 打算发送一条 test-and-set 指令请求到 S1
one is gonna send a test and set request
to server one server one will you know
把它的值设置成 1，并返回旧值 0 给 C1
set it state to one and return the
previous value of zero to client one and
所以 C1 认为它拿到了锁
so that mean client one will think it
如果它是一台 vmware ft 服务器，那它就认为它能接管 primary
has the lock and if it's a VMware ft
server will think it can be takeovers
但是这个副本的值仍然是 0
primarily but this replica still of zero
如果这个客户端 C2 也发送了一条 test-and-set 请求
in it all right so now if client to
who've also sends a test and set request
发送给所有的服务器，但是它发现 S2 挂掉了
to you know what client send them to
both sees that server one appears to be
根据前面的规则，你只要能和其中之一服务器通信就 ok
down follows the rule that says well you
just send to the one server but you can
接下来 C2 会认为它请求到了锁，你也认为它确实是请求到了这把锁
talk to then it will also think that it
would acquire because client you
接下来 C2 会认为它请求到了锁，你也认为它确实是请求到了这把锁
also think that it acquired the lock and
现在想象一下，这台 test-and-server 被用于 vmware ft
so now you know if we were imagining
this test and that server was going to
现在想象一下，这台 test-and-server 被用于 vmware ft
be used with the vmware ft
在没有请求服务器的情况下
然而所有的 vmware 机器都认为它们可以成为 primary
you know both replicas both of these VMware
在没有请求服务器的情况下
然而所有的 vmware 机器都认为它们可以成为 primary
machines I think they could be primary
在没有请求服务器的情况下
然而所有的 vmware 机器都认为它们可以成为 primary
by themselves without consulting the
所以这会导致一个完全错误的结果
other server so that's a complete
对于这种情况，我们要么等待 2 台服务器，放弃容错的功能
failure so with this setup and two
servers it seemed like we had this we
对于这种情况，我们要么等待 2 台服务器，放弃容错的功能
just had to choose either you wait for
both and you're not fault-tolerant or
要么就只等待其中之一的响应，放弃正确性
you wait for just one and you're not
这个错误的版本通常被称为脑裂(split brain)
correct and not correct version
it's often called split brain so
好，还有啥问题没？
everybody see this well
这基本上就是 80 年代末的代表了
so this was basically where things stood
until the late 80s and when people but
但那时候人们也的确是想构建出这样一个复制系统出来
people did want to build replicated
比如用于控制电话交换机的计算机
systems you know like the computers that
control telephone switches or the
又或是运行在银行的那些计算机
computers that ran banks you know there
在这些地方，我们花费了大量的金钱，就是为了保证服务的可靠性
was place when we spend a huge amount
of money in order to have reliable
所以他们会去构建这样的复制系统
service and so they would replicate they
would build replicated systems and the
他们会构建这样的副本
way they would deal the way would that
但是尝试去消除掉脑裂需要一些其它技术
they would have replication but try to
rule out of rule out split brain it's a
但是尝试去消除掉脑裂需要一些其它技术
couple of techniques one is they would
其中之一就是构建一个不会出错的网络
build a network that could not fail and
这什么意思呢？
so usually what that means and in fact
你可以想象使用这样的网络基本上不可能出现故障
you guess use networks that essentially
cannot fail all the time the wires
比如在你的电脑内，CPU 和 DRAM 之间的连接通常都很高效也不会出现故障
inside your laptop you know connecting
the CPU to the DRAM are effectively what
比如在你的电脑内，CPU 和 DRAM 之间的连接通常都很高效也不会出现故障
you know a network that cannot fail
between the between your CPU and DRAM so
所以你可以合理的去假设，大量的烧钱，小心的维护设备
you know with reasonable assumptions and
lots of money and you know sort of
所以你可以合理的去假设，大量的烧钱，小心的维护设备
carefully controlled physical situation
比如你不会在地板上看到乱放的电缆
like you don't want to have a cable
snaking across the floor that somebody
比如你不会在地板上看到乱放的电缆
can step on you know it's got to be
因此你得好好去设计网线的安装方式
physically designed set up with a
如果没有网络故障，那脑裂的问题自然就不会发生
network that cannot fail you can rule
在大量资金保证和这种假设下，就能解决脑裂的问题
out split brain it's bit of an
assumption but with enough money people
在大量资金保证和这种假设下，就能解决脑裂的问题
get quite close to this because if the
假设 C1 无法和 S2 通信，而且网络又不可能发生故障
network cannot fail that basically means
that the client can't talk to a server
那就说明一定是 S2 宕机了
to that means server two must be down
因为你网络不可能发生故障
because it can't have been the network
所以这是一种人们构建没有脑裂的复制系统的一种方式
malfunctioning so that was one way that
people sort of built replication systems
所以这是一种人们构建没有脑裂的复制系统的一种方式
it didn't suffer from split brain
另一种可行的方式就是人类介入
another possibility would be to have
some human beings sort out the problem
比如不要让系统自动的去处理任何事情
that is don't automatically do anything
客户端它总是要去等待所有的服务器响应
instead have the clients you know by
default clients always have to wait for
客户端它总是要去等待所有的服务器响应
you know both replicas to respond or
决不允许只有一台服务器响应的情况下，继续执行
something never allowed to proceed with
just one of them but you can you know
如果发生这种情况，就要拉响警报，拨打值班同学的电话
call somebody's beeper to go off some
值班同学冲进机房，看到 2 个副本
human being goes to the machine room and
sort of looks at the two replicas and
然后将它关机，以确保它确实关闭了
either turns one off to make sure it's
definitely dead
或者检查一下它们其中之一确实已经宕机，另一台还在线
or verifies that one of them has indeed
crashed and if the other is alive and so
你得把人当作断路器
you're essentially using the human as a
as the tie breaker and the human is a
如果把人看作计算机的话，那人又成为了单点故障
you know if they were a computer it
如果把人看作计算机的话，那他们自己又成为了单点故障
would be a single point of failure themselves
所以相当长一段时间人们会使用其它方案来构建复制系统
so for a long time people use
one of the other these schemes in order
所以相当长一段时间人们会使用其它方案来构建复制系统
to build replicated systems and it's not
他们被迫需要做工作，而且人类通常也不能快速做出响应
you know they can be made to work the
humans don't respond very quickly and
让网络不出故障成本又很高
the network that cannot fail is
所以这些方案基本都不太可行
expensive but it's not not doable but it
但是事实证明，我们确实是能构建出能够自动容错，并且能正确工作的系统
turned out that you can actually build
automated failover systems that can work
即使遇上那种诡异的网络故障，在这种网络可以分区(partition)的情况下，也没关系
correctly in the face of flaky networks
of networks that could fail on the can
这种将网络一分为二，两边之间互相无法进行通信
partition so this split of the network
in half where the two sides operate they
通常被称为 partition(分区)
can't talk to each other that's usually
called a partition and the big insight
人们构建自动化的，不受脑裂影响的复制系统的关键是 少数服从多数的投票思想
that people came up with in order to
build automated replication systems that
人们构建自动化的，不受脑裂影响的复制系统的关键是 少数服从多数的投票思想
don't suffer from split brain is the
idea of a majority vote this is a
这种概念在 raft 论文里出现过
concept that shows up in like every
other sentence practically in the raft
这是取得后续进展的基石
paper sort of fundamental way of
第一步，得有奇数台服务器，而不是偶数台
proceeding the first step is to have an
odd number of servers instead of an even
比如这里就有缺陷了，看起来有点太对称了
number of servers like one flaw here is
that it's a little bit too symmetric all
分裂的两边，它们看起来没什么区别
right the two sides of the split here
just they just look the same so they run
它们运行的相同的程序，做着一样的事情
the same software they're gonna do the
这看起来不太好
same thing and that's not good but if
但是如果你有奇数台服务器的话
you have an odd number of servers then
那看起来就一点也不对称了
it's not symmetric anymore right at
在只有一个分裂的网络中，起码是一边有 2 台，另一边只有 1 台
least a single network split will be
presumably two servers on one side and
在只有一个分裂的网络中，起码是一边有 2 台，另一边只有 1 台
one server on the other side and they
它们一点也不对称，这也是多数投票(majority vote)方案所迷人的地方
won't be symmetric at all and that's
part of what majority vote majority
它们一点也不对称，这也是多数投票(majority vote)方案所迷人的地方
voting schemes are appealing to so basic
所以基本思想就是得有奇数台服务器
ideas you have an odd number of servers
为了取得进展，在 raft 的 leader 选举或是日志提交里
in order to make progress of any kind so
in raft elect a leader or cause a log
为了取得进展，在 raft 的 leader 选举或是日志提交里
entry to be committed in order to make
每一步都需要得到大多数的服务器，也就是超过一半的服务器支持
any progress at each step you have to
assemble a majority of the server's more
每一步都需要得到大多数的服务器，也就是超过一半的服务器支持
than half more than half of all the
servers in order to sort of approve that
这样才能让每一步（比如 leader 选举或是日志提交）得以成功执行
step like vote for a leader or accept a
new log entry and commit it so you know
最直白的方式就是有 3 台服务器中有 2 台需要执行这些步骤
the most straightforward way is that two
of three servers required to do anything
这种方式能正确工作的原因是
one reason this works of course is that
如果遇到了 partition
if there's a partition there can't be
绝不可能有超过一个以上的 partiton 同时拥有一半以上的服务器
more than one partition with a majority
of the server's in it that's one way to
举个例子，一个 partition 可以只有一台服务器在里头
look at this a partition can have one
这时它就不是一个 majority 系统
server in it which it's not a majority
又或者这个 partition 里有 2 台服务器，那另一个 parition 一定就只有 1 台了
or maybe you can have two but if one
partition has two then the other
又或者这个 partition 里有 2 台服务器，那另一个 parition 一定就只有 1 台了
partition has to have only one server in
因此也无法聚合成为超过半数以上的服务器，也无法进行下一步操作
it and therefore will never be able to
assemble a majority and won't be able to
需要阐明一点的是，这里所说的大多数
make progress and just to be totally
clear when we're talking about a
需要阐明一点的是，这里所说的大多数
majority it's always a majority out of
是所有服务器（包括在线和宕机的）中的大多数，而不是仅指在线服务器中的大多数
all of the server's not just a live
哈哈，关于这一点曾经也困扰了我相当长一段时间
servers this is the point that confused
me for a long time but if you have a
如果你有 3 台服务器，或许其中有宕机的或是其它故障
system with three servers and maybe some
of them have failed or something if you
构成大多数的服务数据仍然是 3 个中的 2 个
need to assemble in the majority it's
always two out of three even if you know
尽管你知道其中有一台宕机了
that one has failed the majority is
那大多数也还是指 所有服务器总量的大多数
always out of the total number of
有一个更加通用的公式来描述它
servers there's a more general
因为大多数投票系统中，3 个有 2 个同意，就能取得进展
formulation of this because a majority
voting system in which two out of three
因为大多数投票系统中，3 个有 2 个同意，就能取得进展
are required to make progress it can
它能在 1 台服务器宕机的情况下继续存活
survive the failure of one server right
另外 2 台服务器依然能够继续取得进展继续工作
any two servers are enough to make
如果你担心系统的可靠性的话，你可以使用更多的服务器
progress if you need to be able to if
you're you know you worried about how
如果你担心系统的可靠性的话，你可以使用更多的服务器
reliable your servers are or then you
can build systems that have more servers
所以这个通用公式是这样的
and so the more general formulation is
如果你有 2f + 1 台服务器，你就能承受 f 台服务故障
if you have two F + 1 servers then you
can withstand f failures you know
所以如果这里是 3 的话，这里就是 1
so if it's three that means F is one and the system with
这个系统这里有 3 台服务器，因此你就能承受 1 台服务故障
three servers you can tolerate F servers
它仍然能够继续运行
step one failure and still keep going
好，这些东西通常我们称之为 quorum 系统(多数派系统)
all right often these are called quorum
3 个中有 2 个及以上存活，就说明它们是一个 quorum
systems because the two out of three is
sometimes held a quorum okay so one
所以我们提及关于 Majority Voting System(大多数投票系统)
的一个特征就是，至多有一个 parition 拥有大多数
property I've already mentioned about
所以我们提及关于 Majority Voting System(大多数投票系统)
的一个特征就是，至多有一个 parition 拥有大多数
these majority voting systems is that at
所以我们提及关于 Majority Voting System(大多数投票系统)
的一个特征就是，至多有一个 parition 拥有大多数
most one partition can have a majority
因此，如果网络分区，我们就不能让所有的网络分区都能取得进展
and therefore if the networks
partitioned we can't have both halves of
因此，如果网络分区，我们就不能让所有的网络分区都能取得进展
the network making progress another more
另一个比较微妙的事情况是
subtle thing that's going on here is
你总需要得到大多数服务器的同意，才能得以继续进行下一步操作
that if you always need a majority of
the servers to proceed and you go
假设你有一系列的指令，在每一步中你都需要得到大多数的服务的支持
through a sort of succession of
operations in which reach operations
假设你有一系列的指令，在每一步中你都需要得到大多数的服务的支持
somebody assembled a majority like you
比如说给 leader 投票，这里说的是 raft 中的 leader 投票
know votes for leaders or let's say
votes for leaders at raft then at every
在每一步中，你所看到的 majority(大多数服务器里，后面不再翻译)
step the majority you assemble for that
至少有 1 台服务器，它也在上一步中的 majority
step must contain at least one server
that was in the previous majority that
这就是说，任意的 2 个 majority 中，至少会有 1 台服务器是重叠的
is any two majorities overlap in at
least one server and it's really that
这个特点比其它的特点更加重要，且被 raft 所依赖，它能避免脑裂的问题
property more than anything else that
raft is relying on to avoid split brain
举个例子
it's the fact that for example when you
当你执行一次成功的 leader 选举，leader 的选票来自于 majority
have a leader a successful leader
election and leader assembles votes from
这个 majority 保证和上一次的 majority 有重叠
a majority its majority is guaranteed to
这个 majority 保证和上一次的 leader 选举中的 majority 有重叠
overlap with the previous leaders
在这个例子里，新产生的 leader 保证它是知道上一代 leader 的 term 号的
majority and so for example the new
leader is guaranteed to know about the
在这个例子里，新产生的 leader 保证它是知道上一代 leader 的 term 号的
term number used by the previous leader
因为它的 majority 和上一代 leader 的 majority 有所重叠
because it's a majority overlaps with
the previous leaders majority and
上一代 majority 中的每个成员都知道上一代的 leader 的 term 号
everybody in the previous leaders
majority knew about the previous leaders
上一代 majority 中的每个成员都知道上一代的 leader 的 term 号
term number
类似的在 raft 里，上一代的 leader 所提交的数据，也必须出现在 majority 中
similarly anything the previous leader
could have committed must be present in
类似的在 raft 里，上一代的 leader 所提交的数据，也必须出现在 majority 中
a majority of the servers in raft and
因此任意一个新的 leader majority 都至少有 1 台与上次重叠
therefore any new leaders majority must
并且这台机器拥有所有已经提交的来自于上一代 leader 的记录
overlap at at least one server with
every committed entry from the previous
这也是 raft 正确的最大的原因
leader this is a big part of why it is
that raft is correct
关于 majority voting system 大家还有问题吗?
any questions about the general concept
of majority voting systems
添加服务器是可能的
it's possible to add servers
这是可能的，在 raft 论文里，可能是第 6 节就解释了如何添加、变更服务器集合
it's possible intersection something
maybe six in the paper explains how to
这是可能的，在 raft 论文里，可能是第 6 节就解释了如何添加、变更服务器集合
add it or change the set of servers and
在一个长期运行的系统中，比如运行 5 年 10 年的，你可能就需要做这件事
it's possible you need to do it in a
long-running system if you're running
在一个长期运行的系统中，比如运行 5 年 10 年的，你可能就需要做这件事
your system for five ten years you know
你需要在一段时间后更换服务器，比如有些服务永久性的损坏了
you're gonna need to replace the servers
after a while you know one of them fails
又或者升级，或者将它转移到另一个不同的机房
permanently or you upgrade or you move
machine rooms to a different machine
你确实需要做一些支持变更集群的操作
room you really do need to be able to
support changing sets of servers so
当然了，这种事也不会每天都发生，但是它确实很关键
that's a it certainly doesn't happen
every day but it's a critical part of
在长期需要维护的系统中, raft 提供了一种方案
this or a long-term maintainability of
在长期需要维护的系统中, raft 提供了一种方案来处理这种情况
these systems and you know the RAFT
offers sort of pattern themselves on the
在长期需要维护的系统中, raft 提供了一种方案来处理这种情况
back that they have a scheme that deals
with this which as well they might
因为这真的很复杂
because it's complex all right so using
这个想法在 1990 年就被使用了
this idea in about 1990 or so there were
当时有两个系统几乎在同一时间发表这一观点
two systems proposed at about the same
他们意识到，你能使用 majority voting system
time that realized that you could use
this majority voting system to kind of
通过使用 3 台代替 2 台服务器的方法，同时采取投票表决
来解决这种显然无法避免的的脑裂问题
get around the apparent impossibility of
通过使用 3 台代替 2 台服务器的方法，同时采取投票表决
来解决这种显然无法避免的的脑裂问题
avoiding split brain by using basically
通过使用 3 台代替 2 台服务器的方法，同时采取投票表决
来解决这种显然无法避免的的脑裂问题
by using three servers instead of two
通过使用 3 台代替 2 台服务器的方法，同时采取投票表决
来解决这种显然无法避免的的脑裂问题
and taking majority votes and in one of
出现的比较早的就是 Paxos，raft 对此也讨论了许多
these very early systems was called
出现的比较早的就是 PAXOS，raft 对此也讨论了许多
Paxos the RAFT paper talks about this a
另一个非常早的系统称为 View-Stamped Replication(VSR)
lot and another of these very early
systems was called View-Stamped Replication
缩写为 VSR
a abbreviation View-Stamped Replication
尽管 PAXOS 是更加被广为人知的系统
and even though Paxos
is by far the more widely known
尽管 PAXOS 是更加被广为人知的系统
system in this department raft is
实际上 raft 在设计上更加接近 VSR
actually closer to design in design to
View-Stamped Replication
这是咱们 MIT 的大佬们发明的（自豪）
which was invented by people at MIT and
所以这些系统都经历了数十年的历史
so there's a sort of a long many decade
history of these systems and they only
大约在 15 年前（现在是 2020 年），它们才开始被用于大型分布式系统
really came to the forefront and started
being used a lot in deployed big
大约在 15 年前（现在是 2020 年），它们才开始被用于大型分布式系统
distributed systems about 15 years
自它们被发明以来，这 15 年它们都表现的非常棒
ago a good 15 years after they were
originally invented okay so let me talk
okay，接下来就要开始讨论 raft 啦
about raft now
raft 以 lib 库的形式被链接到某些服务器程序中
raft is a takes the form of a library
intended to be included in some service
所以，如果你有一个复制服务
application so if you have a replicated
每一个副本都会添加一些类似 rpc 的代码然后再加上 raft 库
service that each of the replicas in the
service is gonna be some application
每一个副本都会添加一些类似 rpc 的代码然后再加上 raft 库
code which you know receives rpcs or
something plus a raft library and the
接下来 raft 库会互相协作来维护 replication
raft libraries cooperate with each other
to maintain replication
这里我们先了解一下单个 raft 副本的软件架构
so sort of software overview of a single
在最上层，我们可以思考一下副本有哪些代码
raft replica is that at the top we can
think of the replicas having the
在 lab3 中，它是一个 key-value 服务器
application code so it might be for lab
3 a key-value server so maybe we have
这个 kv 数据库它是有状态的
some key value server and it has state the
也就是应用程序是有状态的，raft 可以帮助它管理复制状态
application has state that raft is
helping it manage replicated state and
对于 kv 服务器，通常它有一张表格来记录 key value
for a key value server it's going to be
a table of keys and values the next
下面这一层是 raft 层
layer down is a raft layer so the key
所以 kv 服务器会发起函数调用进入到 raft
value server is gonna sort of make
function calls into raft and they're
他们之间会反复通信几次，raft 会保持一些状态
gonna chitchat back and forth a little
bit and raft keeps a little bit of state
你可以在图 2 中看到
you can see it in Figure 2 and
raft 中最关键的一个地方就是它有一个记录所有操作的 log 日志
our purpose really the most critical piece
of state is that raft has a log of
现在我们拥有一个 3 副本的复制系统
operations and a system with 3 replicas
we're actually gonna have you
它们 3 都有着完全相同的结构
know 3 servers that have exactly the
same identical structure and hopefully
在每一层都希望它们有完全相同的数据
the very same data sitting in sitting at
both layers
在这外面，还有一些客户端
right outside of this there's gonna be
游戏是这样的，我们有客户端 C1, C2
clients and the game is that so we have
you know client 1 and client two whole
clients 不必知道它和谁去通信
bunch of clients the clients don't
它只需要增加一些加上一些外部的（lib 库) 的代码就能使用服务
really know the clients are you know
just external code that needs to be able
它只需要增加一些加上一些外部的（lib 库) 的代码就能使用服务
to use the service and the hope is the
我们希望 clients 不用关心它到底是同哪一个副本服务通信
clients won't really need to be aware
that they're talking to a replicated
而是要让它看起来像是只和一个服务器通信
service that to the clients that are
looking almost like it's just one server
而是要让它看起来像是只和一个服务器通信
and they talked with one server and so
clients 把 key 发送到当前 leader 的 application layer(应用层)
leader 指的是 raft 中的 leader
the clients actually send client
clients 把 key 发送到当前 leader 的 application layer(应用层)
leader 指的是 raft 中的 leader
requests to the key to the application
clients 把 key 发送到当前 leader 的 application layer(应用层)
leader 指的是 raft 中的 leader
layer of the current leader the replica
clients 把 key 发送到当前 leader 的 application layer(应用层)
leader 指的是 raft 中的 leader
that's the current leader in raft and so
接下来应用层请求这个 key-value 数据库
these are gonna be you know application
level requests for a database for a key
可能是 put 和 get 请求
value server these might be put and get
put 请求就是用 key 和 value 来更新这个 table
requests you know put takes a key and a
value and updates the table and get
get 就是根据当前的 key 来查询当前的 value
asked the service to get the current key
current value corresponding to some key
看起来 raft 好像在这里啥也没干
so this like has nothing about to do
with raft it's just sort of
就只有简单的 client 和 server 之间的交互
client-server interaction for whatever
service we're building but once one of
但是一旦这些请求被 client 发送到 server，会发生什么事？
these commands gets sent from the
requests get sent from the clients of
但是一旦这些请求被 client 发送到 server，会发生什么事？
the server what actually happens is you
在非副本服务器上，应用层代码执行这条请求并更新这个 table
know on a non replicated server the
application code would like execute this
在非副本服务器上，应用层代码执行这条请求并更新这个 table
request and say update the table and
然后回复这条 put 请求，但是在 raft 副本服务器上不是这样的
response to a put but not in a raft
假设 client 发送了一条请求到 leader 上
replicated service instead if assuming
the client sends a request to leader
应用层会把请求向下透传到 raft 层
what really happens is the application
layer simply sends the request the
应用层会把请求向下透传到 raft 层
clients request down into the raft layer
说，Hi 伙计，这儿有一条请求，请把它提交到 replicated log(复制日志)里
to say look you know here's a request
please get it committed into the
啥时候你搞定了，再通知我一下
replicated log and tell me when you're
此时 raft 会互相进行通信
done and so at this point the rafts
直到半数以上的副本把这条操作添加到各自的日志中，表示它已经复制完成
chitchat with each other until all the
replicas are a majority the replicas get
直到半数以上的副本把这条操作添加到各自的日志中，表示它已经复制完成
this new operation into their logs said
当 leader 知道所有副本完成复制后，只有在这个时候，raft 才会向上面的 kv 层发送通知
it is replicated and then when its
and leader knows that all of the replicas of
当 leader 知道所有副本完成复制后，只有在这个时候，raft 才会向上面的 kv 层发送通知
a copy of this only then as a raft sent
a notification up back up to the key
说，啊哈，你 1 分钟前发我的那条操作
value layer saying aha that operation
you sent me a minute ago
现在已经提交到所有的副本中去了，它已经被安全的复制了
it's been now committed into all the
replicas and so it's safely replicated
此时应用层就可以执行这条操作了
and at this point it's okay to execute
that operation the raft you know the
raft... client 把请求把送给 kv 层
client sends a request with the key
value layer key value layer does not
kv 层还没有执行，所以我们也不能保证它会执行
execute it yet so we're not sure because
因为这条操作尚未被复制，只有它被复制到所有副本中的时候，raft 才会通知 leader
it hasn't been replicated only when it's
in all and the logs of all the replicas
因为这条操作尚未被复制，只有它被复制到所有副本中的时候，raft 才会通知 leader
then raft notifies the leader now the
这时候 leader 才会真正的执行这条操作
leader actually execute the operation
对于 put 请求，就是更新这个 kv table
which corresponds to you know for a put updating the key-value table
对于 get 请求，就是读取这个正确的 value 值
for a get reading correct
最后会发送一个回复消息给客户端
value out of the table and then finally
sends the reply back to the client so
这就是个普通操作
that's the ordinary operation of the...
超过半数被复制就会提交的
it's committed when it's in a majority and
为什么不能是所有副本复制完再提交的原因是
again the reason why I can't be all is
如果我们想构建这样一个容错系统
that if we want to build a
它就必须有能力保证在部分服务宕机的情况下，也要保证系统正常运行
fault-tolerant system it has to be able
to make progress even if some of the
它就必须有能力保证在部分服务宕机的情况下，也要保证系统正常运行
server's have failed so yeah so ever
所以有超过半数以上的副本都复制后，就能提交了
so it's committed when it's in a majority
[提问]
sorry，是的，还有一个额外的步骤是当所有操作被提交时
sorry，yeah and so in addition when operations
每一个副本都会向上层发送所有操作
finally committed each of the replicas
sends the operation up each of the raft
每个 raft 层都会向上层的本地的应用发送操作
library layer sends the operation up to
the local application layer in the local
本地应用层会把所有操作应用到它的状态上
application layer applies that operation
to its state its state and so they all
所有的副本都能看到相同的操作序列
so hopefully all the replicas seem the
same stream of operations they show up
这些向上的调用顺序都是一致的，并且以相同的顺序被应用到状态中
in these up calls in the same order they
get applied to the state in the same
假设所有这些操作都是确定性的
order and you know assuming the
假设所有这些操作都是确定性的，最好是这样
operations are deterministic which they
better be the state of the replicas
在所有的副本上，副本的状态都是一样的
replicated State will of all in
identically on all the replicas so
典型的，这里这个 table 就是论文里说的 state
typically this this table is what the
paper is talking about when it talks
咱们换种方式来看这个交互过程
about state a different way of viewing
this interaction and one that'll sort of
其中之一是这门课里将会多次提到的一种记号，时序图
notation that will come up a lot in this
course is that a sort of time diagram
我待会儿画个给你看看，时序图里，消息是怎么传递的
I'll draw you a time diagram of how the
假设有个 client(C1)，S1(leader), S2 和 S3
messages work so let's imagine we have a
client and server one is the leader that
假设有个 client(C1)，S1(leader), S2 和 S3
we also have server to server three and
朝下的方向表示时间流逝
time flows downward on this diagram we
client 发送一条原始请求到 S1
imagine the client sending the original
request to server one after that server
S1 的 raft 层发送一条 AppendEntries RPC 到另 2 个副本
ones raft layer sends an append entries
RPC to each of the two replicas this is
这里是个普通的 put 请求
just an ordinary I'll say a put request
这里是 AppendEntries 请求
this is append entries requests the
这个 server 现在正在等待回复
server is now waiting for replies and
S1 只要收到了半数以上节点的回复（包括它自己)
the server's from other replicas as soon
as replies from a majority arrive back
S1 只要收到了半数以上节点的回复（包括它自己)
including the leader itself so in a
在这个仅有 3 副本的系统里
system with only three replicas because the
leader 只要收到了其它任意一台副本的对 AppendEntries 的响应，就构成了 majority
leader only has to wait for one other
replica to respond positively to an
leader 只要收到了其它任意一台副本的对 AppendEntries 的响应，就构成了 majority
append entries as soon as it assembles
positive responses from a majority
leader 执行 put 或 get 命令，并回复结果
the leader
leader 执行 put 或 get 命令，并回复结果给 client
execute a command figures out what the
answer is like put or get
leader 执行 put 或 get 命令，并回复结果给 client
and sends the reply back to the client
同时，你知道，S3 实际上还是在线的，它也会回复它的结果
and meanwhile of course you know S3
actually alive it'll send back its
但是我们并不需要等待它的回复了
response too but we're not waiting for
这个对理解图 2 来说很有用
it although it's useful to know and
大家看到的这些就是对于没有异常情况下的普通操作
figure 2 all right everybody see this
this is the sort of ordinary operation
大家看到的这些就是对于没有异常情况下的普通操作
of the system no no failures
Oh gosh，是的，我好像遗漏了一个重要步骤
oh gosh yeah I like I left out important
你知道，在这个时候，leader 知道大多数的副本已经把这条操作添加到了日志中了
steps so you know this point the leader
knows oh I got you know majority
我可以现在可以执行客户端发来的命令，并回复 yes
put it into log I can go ahead and
execute it and reply yes to the client
因为它(leader)提交了，但是 S2 还啥也不知道
because it's committed but server two
doesn't know anything yet it just knows
它只知道，我从 leader 得到了一条请求，但是我不知道 leader 是否提交了它
well you know I got this request from
the leader but I don't know if it's
leader 是否提交依赖于，比如说依赖 S2 的回复是否被 leader 收到
committed yet depends on for example
whether my reply got back to the leader
比如说 S2 的回复在网络中丢失，leader 就收不到回复
for all server 2 knows it's reply was
drop by the network maybe the leader
leader 因此也就决不会提交这条请求
never heard the reply and never decided
to commit this request so there's
实际上这里还有另一个阶段还没讲
actually another stage once the server
一旦 leader 意识到请求被提交，那么它就需要通知其它的副本这个事实
realizes that a request is committed it
then needs to tell the other replicas that fact
所以这里还有一条额外的消息
and so there are there's
there's an extra message here exactly
这条消息是什么，依赖于发生了什么事情
what that message is depends a little
bit on what what else is going on it's
至少在 raft 中，并不存在这样一条日志提交的消息
at least in raft there's not an explicit
commit message instead the information
取而代之，leader 会在下一次的 AppendEntries 中，记录一些信息，然后发送出去
is piggybacked inside the next append
entries that leader sends out the next
取而代之，leader 会在下一次的 AppendEntries 中，记录一些信息，然后发送出去
append entries RPC it sends out for
不管是什么原因，像 leader commit 或是别的什么东西，都会填充到 RPC 中
whatever reason like there's a commit
leader commit or something filled in that
在下次 leader 需要发送 heartbeat(心跳)的时候
RPC and the next time the leader needs
have to send a heartbeat heartbeat or
或是需要发送一条新的客户端请求的时候
needs to send out a new client request
because some different client requests
会把 leader 最新的 commit 值连带发送出去
or something it'll send out the new higher
leader commit value and at that point
在那时候，副本就会去执行这些操作，应用到各自的状态机中
the replicas will execute the operation
and apply it to their state yes
是的，这个协议有相当多的的通信
oh yes so this is a this is a protocol
that has a quite a bit of chitchat in it
并且它的速度也不怎么快
and it's not super fast indeed you know
你知道，客户端发送请求到 server，然后 server 同其它实例通信
yeah client sends in request request has
to get to the server the server talks to
你知道，客户端发送请求到 server，然后 server 同其它实例通信
at least you know another instance that
这中间有多条请求的响应都需要进行等待
multiple messages has to wait for the
responses send something back so there's
而且这里好几轮消息需要来回发送多次
a bunch of message round-trip times
and added here
是的，实际上这取决于你的实现
yes if so this is up to you as the
当 leader 把最新的 commitIndex 发送出去后
implementer actually exactly when the
leader sends out the updated commit
如果客户端只是偶尔发送一条请求
index if client requests a comeback only
very occasionally then you know the
leader 或许就会发送 heartbeat 或是发送一条特殊的 AppendEntries 消息
leader may want to send out a heartbeat
or send out a special append entries
如果客户端请求相当频繁，那也没关系
message if client requests come quite
frequently then it doesn't matter
因为如果每秒在上千条请求到来
because if they come you know there's
thousand arrive per second oh jesus
oh, 天呐，这真的是相当的快
it'll be very longer very soon and
所以你可以不用单独再生成一条额外的消息去通知其它副本，这个代价太高了
so you can piggyback so without
generating an extra message which is
所以你只要把你的信息放在下一条消息里就行了
somewhat expensive you can get the
information out on the next message you
所以你只要把你的信息放在下一条消息里就行了
were gonna send anyway in fact I I don't
事实上，我认为副本执行请求的时间点并不是关键
think the time at which the replicas
execute the request is critical because
因为没有人需要等待它的返回结果
nobody's waiting for it at least if
至少在在没有异常的情况下是这样
there's no failures if there's no
如果没有异常，副本执行请求就不在关键路径中
failures replicas executing the request
isn't really on the critical path like
比如客户端并不需要去等待它们（其它副本）
the client isn't waiting for them the
而是等待 leader 执行完
client is waiting for the leader to
所以它并不会影响客户端的延时
execute so it may not be that it may not
affect client perceived latency sort of
严格来说，这就是它的工作方式
exactly how this gets staged
好，还有一个必须要正视的问题
all right one question you should ask is
为什么系统要如此关注 log(日志)，日志又是用来干什么的？
why does the system why is the system so
focused on logs what are the logs doing
尝试找出这个问题的答案是有意义，有价值的
and it's sort of worth trying to come up
with an explicit answers to that one
日志如此重要的原因是，它是一种机制
answer to why the system is totally
focused on logs is that the log is the
通过这个机制，leader 可以维护操作的顺序
kind of mechanism by which the leader
这个顺序对复制状态机业说非常重要
orders operations it's vital for these
replicated state machines that all the
所有的副本，不仅仅要应用客户端的同样的请求操作
replicas apply not just the same client
operations to their start but the same
而且还要以相同的顺序去执行
operations in the same order but they
所有来自客户端的请求操作，都要以相同的顺序在不同副本上执行
all have to apply that these operations
coming from the clients in the same
在众多的事情中，日志也是复制状态机的一部分
order and the log among many other
things is part of the machinery by which
通过它，leader 可以安排客户端请求操作的顺序
the or the leader assigns an order to
the incoming client operations I give
如果有 10 个客户端并发请求 leader
you know ten clients send operations to
the leader at the same time the client
leader 需要选择一个顺序，确保所有的副本都要遵守这个顺序
the leader has to pick pick an order
make sure everybody all the replicas
事实上，日志包含了一个一个编号的槽
obey that order and the log is you know
the fact that the log has numbered slots
它包含了 leader 传送过来的操作顺序
this part have a leader expresses the
order it's chosen another use of the log
日志的另一个用途是，从这里到这里这个时间中间
is that between this point and this
S3 收到了 leader 发来的操作，但是它不确定该操作是否已经提交
point server 3 has received an operation
that it is not yet sure is committed and
因此它还不能去执行，它必须把这条操作暂存起来
it cannot execute it yet it has to put
the this operation aside somewhere until
直到接收到 leader 的 commit 号增长这条消息
the increment to the leader commit value
所以 log 另一个作用是，对于 follower 来说
comes in and so another thing that the
log is doing is that on the followers
日志是 follwer 用于暂存操作的地方，这些操作都是暂定的
the log is the place where the follower
sort of sets aside operations that are
日志是 follwer 用于暂存操作的地方，这些操作都是暂定的
still tentative that have arrived but
虽然已经收到了，但是还不确定是否可以提交
are not yet known to be committed and
他们也可能会把它丢弃掉，后面我们将会看到这种情况
they may have to be thrown away as we'll
所以这是另一种用法
see so that's another use I'm the I sort
leader 使用日志是因为 leader 需要把操作记录在日志里
of do log that use on the leader side
is that the leader needs to remember
leader 使用日志是因为 leader 需要把操作记录在日志里
operations in its log because it may
在部分 follower 离线时，可以进行重传
need to retransmit them to followers if
some followers offline maybe it's
比如网络发生短暂的故障或是消息丢失了
something briefly happened to its
network
比如网络发生短暂的故障或是消息丢失了
action or something misses some messages
leader 就要有能力重新发送 follower 错过的日志消息
the leader needs to be able to resend
log messages that any followers missed
所以 leader 需要有这么一个地方来保存客户端请求的 copy
and so the leader needs a place where
can set aside copies of messages of
即使这些请求已经被执行过
client requests even ones that it's already executed
就是为了能够把它们重传给 client(似乎口误)
in order to be able to
resend them to the client I mean resend
我意思是把他们重传给丢失了部分操作的副本（纠正了一下）
them to replicas that missed missed that
最后一个他们保存日志的原因，至少在图 2 所描述的
operation and a final reason for all of
最后一个保存日志的原因，至少在图 2 所描述的
them to keep the log is that at least in
the world of figure 2 if a server
如果一个 server 宕机后重启，并重新加入，那就需要这些日志
crashes and restarts and wants to rejoin
如果你确实需要一台宕机的 server 启动并重新加入 raft 集群的话
and you really need if it you really
want a server that crashes - in fact we
如果你确实需要一台宕机的 server 启动并重新加入 raft 集群的话
start and rejoin the raft cluster
如果不能重新加入，你现在可操作的机器就只剩下 3 台中的 2 台
otherwise you're now operating with only
two out of three servers and you can't
假设再发生点故障，你就无法容错了
survive any more failures we need to
所以我们需要能把失败的机器重启并重新加入集群
reincorporate failed and rebooted
server 在重新启动之后，会使用持久化在磁盘上的日志
servers and the log is sort of where or
what a server rebooted server uses the
server 在重新启动之后，会使用持久化在磁盘上的日志
log persisted to its disk because one of
因为有一条规则是每个 raft server 需要把它的日志写入磁盘
the rules is that each raft server needs
to write its log to its disk where it
这样即使它在宕机后，日志仍然存在
will still be after it crashes and
重启之后，server 会使用，并对日志中的操作从头进行重演
restarts that log is what the server
重启之后，server 会使用日志中的操作，从头进行重演
uses or replays the operations in that
log from the beginning to sort of create
直到创建出宕机之前的状态，然后继续运行
its state as of when it crashed and then
then it carries on from there so the log
所以 log 也会被用于持久化，将来用于重建状态
is also used as part of the persistence
plan as a sequence of commands to
所以 log 也会被用于持久化，将来用于重建状态
rebuild the state
好吧，最后还是有人问了。。。问题是说
well ultimately okay so the question is
假设 leader 有能力每秒处理 1000 个客户端的命令
suppose the leader is capable of
executing a thousand client commands a
但是 follower 每秒只能处理 100 个客户端命令
second and the followers are only
incapable of executing a hundred client
但是 follower 每秒只能处理 100 个客户端命令
commands per second that's sort of
这是它能处理的最大速率
sustained rate you know full speed v so
其中一件事要注意的是
one thing to note is that the the
副本，也就是 follower 在执行命令前需要先进行确认
replicas the followers acknowledge
commands before they execute them so
在它们的日志中，确认和累积的速率是不受限制的
the rate at which they acknowledge
and accumulate stuff in their logs is
所以它们可能会一秒一次确认 1000 条请求
not limited so you know maybe they can
acknowledge that a thousand requests per
如果它们一直这样做，将会导致日志大小没有上限
second if they do that forever then they
will build up unbounded size logs
因为它们执行的速率远远落后于 leader 发送请求的速率
because their execution rate falls it
will fall on an unbounded amount behind
因为它们执行的速率远远落后于 leader 发送请求的速率
the rate at which the leader has given
在我们的游戏规则里，这意味着它们最终会在某个时间点耗尽内存
the messages sort of under the rules of
our game and so what that means they
在我们的游戏规则里，这意味着它们最终会在某个时间点耗尽内存
will eventually run out of memory at
当它落后 10 亿条日志后
some point so after they have a billion
after they fall a billion log entries
内存分配器再为新的日志条目分配内存就会失败
behind those just like they'll call the
memory allocator for space for a new
内存分配器再为新的日志条目分配内存就会失败
log entry and it will fail so yeah and
是的，Raft 不具备流量控制来处理这样的情况
Raft doesn't Raft doesn't have the flow
controls that's required to cope with
所以我认为，在真实的系统中
this so I think in a real system you
你知道可能会使用 piggyback
(piggyback 捎带消息，就是前面讲过的，把消息放到下一次请求中一起发出去)
would actually need you know probably
并且它也不需要那么的实时
piggybacked and doesn't need to be
在这里，你可能需要一些额外的通信来表明执行到哪里了
real-time but you probably need some
kind of additional communication here
在这里，你可能需要一些额外的通信来表明执行到哪里了
that says well here's how far I've
这样便于 leader 发现，哦，我领先 follwer 上千条请求了
gotten in execution so that the leader
can say well you know too many thousands
这样便于 leader 发现，哦，我领先 follwer 上千条请求了
of requests ahead of the point in which
the followers have executed yes I think
在生产系统中，这种领先可能会推进到系统绝对最大值（达到系统上限)
there's probably you know in a
在生产系统中，这种领先可能会推进到系统绝对最大值（达到系统上限
production system that you're trying to
此时你就需要一些额外的信息来限制 leader，防止它领先太多
push to the absolute max you would you
might well need an extra message to
此时你就需要一些额外的信息来限制 leader，防止它领先太多
throttle the leader if it got too far
ahead
okay，问题是说如果这些 server 之一宕机
okay so the question is if if one of
these servers crashes it has this log
图 2 有一条规则说，日志需要持久化到磁盘上
that it persisted to disk because that's
one of the rules of figure two so the
所以 server 可以从磁盘上就可以恢复出日志
server will be able to be just logged
当然了，server 并不知道当前日志已经执行到哪里
back from disk but of course that server
doesn't know how far it got in executing
至少第一次刚启动的时候它是不知道的
the log and also it doesn't know at
least when it first reboots by the rule
根据图 2 的规则，它甚至不知道日志提交了多少
that figure two it doesn't even know how
much of the log is committed so the
所以你的问题的答案是，如果一个 server 在宕机后重新启动
first answer to your question is that
immediately after a restart you know
所以你的问题的答案是，如果一个 server 在宕机后重新启动
after a server crashes and restarts and
它会读取它的日志，除此之外它什么也不能做
reads its log it is not allowed to do
anything with the log because it does
因为它不知道日志提交到多远的位置
not know how far the system has
committed in its log maybe as long as
也许是 1000 条没有提交，0 条已提交
has a thousand uncommitted entries and
zero committed entries for all it notes
也许是 1000 条没有提交，0 条已提交
so
如果 leader 挂了，当然就没什么用了
if a leader die of course that doesn't
但是我们可以假设，如果他们全宕机了
help either but let's suppose they've
这对我来说有点超纲了
all crashed this is getting ahead of its
getting a bit ahead of me but well
不过还是假设它们都宕机了
suppose they've all crashed and so all
图 2 显示，它们持有的状态被标记为非易失的
they have is the state that was marked
as non-volatile in figure 2 which
还包括日志，好像还有最新的 term(任期号)
includes the log and maybe the latest
所以它们不知道……如果他们全宕机了
term and so they don't know some if
there's a crash but they all crash and
它们当中没有人能知道它们曾经执行到了什么地方
they always start none of them knows
initially how far they had been have
它们当中没有人能知道它们曾经执行到了什么地方
executed before the crash so what
所以接下来就会发生 leader 选举
happens is that you leader election one
它们当中之一会选择一个 leader 出来
of them gets picked as a leader and that
leader if you sort of track through what
图 2 中会解释，AppendEntries 是如何工作的
figure 2 says about how AppendEntries
is supposed to work the leader will
leader 实际上会从发送AppendEntries
actually figure out as a byproduct of
发送心跳带来的副产品中断定一些信息
sending out AppendEntries sending out the
first heartbeat really it'll
它能够推断出最新的提交位置
figure out what the latest point is
也就是半数以上的副本都能对它们的日志达成一致的位置
basically that that all of the that a
majority of the replicas agree on their
因为这就是提交的位置
logs because that's the commit point
另一种看待方式是
another way of looking at it is that
一旦你选择了一个 leader
once you choose a leader through the
通过 AppendEntries 机制
append entries mechanism the leader
leader 会强制所有其它副本和 leader 有完全相同的日志
forces all of the other replicas to have
identical logs to the leader and at that
在这一点，论文作了一些解释
point plus a little bit of extra the
paper explains at that point since the
由于 leader 知道它强制让所有副本拥有相同的日志
leader knows that it's forced all the
replicas to have logs
由于 leader 知道它强制让所有副本拥有相同的日志
that are identicals to it then it knows
它知道有半数以上的副本都拥有这些日志项
that all the replicas must also have a
there must be a majority of replicas
它知道有半数以上的副本都拥有这些日志项
with that all those log entires in that
这些日志是完全相同的，也必须是已被提交的
logs which are now are identical must
因为它们被半数以上的副本所持有
also be committed because they're held
on a majority of replicas and at that
在这一点，leader……
point a leader you know the append
图 2 中描述的，针对 leader 的 AppendEntires 代码
entries code described in Figure 2 for
会递增 leader 的提交点
the leader will increment the leaders
所有人现在都能从头开始执行完整的日志
commit point and everybody can now
execute the entire log from the
从 0 开始重建他们的状态
beginning and recreate their state from
这可能相当的费时
scratch possibly extremely laborious
所以这就是图 2 中所说的
so that's what figure two says it's
显然从 0 开始执行，显的有点不太吸引人
obviously this be executing from scratch
is not very attractive but it's where
但是这就是基础协议规定要做的
the basic protocol does and we'll see
不过明天我们能看到一个更高效的版本
tomorrow that the the sort of version of
this is more efficient to use as
它使用 checkpoint 机制，咱们明天会讲
checkpoints and we'll talk about tomorrow
okay，这就是普通的没异常的情况下的执行步骤
okay so this was a sequence in
sort of ordinary non failure operation
另一件事是我想简单介绍下 raft 接口长啥样
another thing I want to briefly mention
is what this interface looks like you've
你们可能做 lab 的时候已经看到过了
probably all seen a little bit of it due
to working on the labs but roughly
粗略来说，这里有一个 key-value 层，这里有它的状态
speaking if you have let's say that this
key value layer with its state and the
raft 层在它之下
raft layer underneath it there's on each
在每个副本中，有 2 个非常重要的接口
replica there's really two main pieces
of the interface between them there's
如果客户端发送请求过来，那么 key-value 层可以使用这个接口请求 raft 层
this method by which the key value layer
can relay if a client sends in a request
key-value 层必须把它传递给 raft
the key value layer has to give it to
说: Hi, raft, 请把这条请求放到日志的某个地方
raft and say please you know fit this
request into the log somewhere and
这个函数是 start(command)，后面你会在 raft.go 文件里看到它
that's the start function that you'll
它只有一个参数，即客户端请求来的命令，它就是个 key-value 对
see in raft.go and really just takes one
argument the client command the key
start 函数会把这条命令放进 log，然后通知调用方日志何时被提交
value they're saying please I got this
command to get into the log and tell me
start 函数会把这条命令放进 log，然后通知调用方日志何时被提交
when it's committed and the other piece
另一方面，调用此函数后，raft 层过会儿通知 key-value 层
of the interface is that by and by the
raft layer will notify the key value
啊哈：刚刚你通过 start 命令发我的操作
layer that AHA that operation that you
sent to me in a start command a while
注意了，不一定就是最近调用的那个 start
ago which may well not be the most
recent start right there you know a
在任意一条日志被提交前，可能同时有 100 个客户端发起请求，并调用 start 函数
hundred client commands could come in
and cause calls to start before any of
在任意一条日志被提交前，可能同时有 100 个客户端发起请求，并调用 start 函数
them are committed so by and by this
这里有一条向上的通信，它通过 go channel 发送一条消息
upward communication is takes the form
of a message on a go channel that the
raft 库向 channel 一端发送，key-value 层从另一端读取
raft library sends on and key value
layer is supposed to read from so
所以这里的 apply，被称之为 apply channel
there's this apply called the apply
在它之上你可以发送 apply 消息
channel and on it on it you send apply message
start 函数，当然了，你需要……
this start and of course you need the
key-value 层需要将 apply channel 接收到的消息同调用的 start 函数做匹配
the key value layer needs to be able to
match up message that receives an apply
key-value 层需要将 apply channel 接收到的消息同调用的 start 函数做匹配
channel with calls to start that it made
start 函数会返回足够的信息，以确保可以做匹配工作
and so the start command actually
returns enough information for that
它会返回 index(索引号)
matchup to happen it returns the index
start 函数最重要的工作就是返回 log 中的 index
that start functions basically returns
the index in the log where if this
如果这条命令被提交了（也可能不会被提交）
command is committed which it might not
那么它将来就会在这个 index 上被提交
be it'll be committed at this index and
我认为，它还会返回当前的任期号，还有一些别的东西，不过不用太关注
I think it also returns the current term
and some other stuff we don't care about
然后，这里的 ApplyMsg 将会包含 index 以及 command
very much and then this apply message is
going to contain the index command and
所有的副本都将拿到这些 apply 消息
all the replicas will get these apply
所以他们就知道，oh, 我应该要 apply 这条命令
messages so they'll all know oh I
should apply this command figure out
我要理解这些命令的含义，然后把它应用到本地的状态里
what this command means and apply it to
my local state and they also get the
同样的，他们可以拿到这个 index，它只在上 leader 有用
index the index is really only useful on the leader
所以它能理解客户端正在发什么请求
so it can figure out what
client would what client requests were talking about
这个问题的答案，有一点点不同
the answer a slightly different question
我们假设客户端发送了做任意的请求，不管它是 put 还是 get，无所谓
let's suppose the client sends any
request in let's say it's a put or a get
我们假设客户端发送了做任意的请求，不管它是 put 还是 get，无所谓
could be put or again it doesn't really
假设就是 GET，在这个位置客户端发送请求，然后等待响应
matter I'd say it to get the point in
which the it's a client sense and again
假设就是 GET，在这个位置客户端发送请求，然后等待响应
and waits for a response the point at
>>> leader 将会在这个位置发送响应，而不是在 leader 得知命令被提交之后
which the leader will send a response not at
leader 将会在这个位置发送响应，而不是在 leader 得知命令被提交之后
all is after the leader knows that
command is committed so this is going to
所以这里将会是 get 的回复
be a sort of get reply so the client
所以客户端看不到任何东西返回
doesn't see anything back I mean and so
这里意思是说，根据实际的 software stack(key-value 层和 raft 层形成的上下关系)
that means in terms of the actual
software stack that means that the key
RPC 将到到达 key-value 层，然后调用 start 函数
value the RPC will arrive the key value
layer will call the start function the
然后 start 函数返回到 key-value 层
start function will return to the key
但是 key-value 层还不会返回给客户端
value layer but the key value layer will
not yet reply to the client because it
因为它不知道这条命令是否有效
does not know if it's good actually it
实际上它还现在没执行客户端请求
hasn't executed the clients request now
它甚至都不知道它是否会执行
it doesn't even know if it ever will
因为它无法保证这条请求是否被提交
because it's not sure if the request is
going to be committed right in the
比如它可能没有被提交
situation which may not be committed is
假设 key-value 层调用 start，在 start 返回后立即宕机了
if the key value layer you know guess
the request calls start and immediately
假设 key-value 层调用 start，在 start 返回后立即宕机了
after start return to crashes right
当然它还没发送它的 apply，append 消息或是别的东西
certainly hasn't sent out its apply what
append messages or whatever
什么也没有进行提交
nothing's be committed yep so so the
所以 raft 中的规则是，当 start 函数返回
game is start returns time passes the
过一段时间后，当和客户端请求相一致的 apply 消息
relevant apply message corresponding to
that client request appears to the key
通过 apply channel 传递到 key-value 服务层的时候
value server on the apply channel and
只有在这个时候，key-value 服务层才会执行请求，并发送 reply
only then and that causes the key value
server to execute the request and send reply
这一切都非常重要
and that's like all this is very
如果一切都正常进行，这没什么大不了的
important when it doesn't really matter
if all everything goes well but if
但是如果有故障产生，你知道，我们要担心错误
there's a failure we're now you know the point
we worrying about failure I
我的意思是说，我们更应该关心：如果产生错误，客户端会看到什么
mean extremely interested in if there
was a failure what did the client see
好，还有一件事，你们也需要非常熟练
all right and so one thing that does
come up is that all of you should be
好，还有一件事，你们也需要非常熟练
familiar with this that at least
思考一下，各副本上的日志可能会产生不一致
initially one interesting thing about
the logs is that they may not be
有很多情况会导致不一致
identical there are a whole bunch of
至少在短时间内，不同副本的结尾的地方可能会产生分叉
situations in which at least for brief
periods of time the ends of the
至少在短时间内，不同副本的结尾的地方可能会产生分叉
different replicas logs may diverge like
比如，如果一个 leader 发起一轮 AppendMessage
for example if a leader starts to send
out a round of append messages but
但是在发送完所有消息前宕机了
crashes before it's able to send all
这意味着有些副本会拿到 append 消息，然后追加到日志中
them out you know that'll mean that some
of the replicas that got the append
这意味着有些副本会拿到 AppendMessage，然后追加到日志中
message will append you know that new
而另一些副本拿不到 AppendMessage RPC，所以不会追加它们
log entry and the ones that didn't get
that append messages RPC won't have
所以很容易明白，日志有时候分产生分叉
appended them so it's easy to see that
the logs are I'm gonna diverge sometimes
好消息是，在一段时间后，raft 实际上最终会强制让日志变得完全相同
the good news is that the the way a raft
works actually ends up forcing the logs
好消息是，在一段时间后，raft 实际上最终会强制让日志变得完全相同
to be identical after a while there may
尽管会存在短暂的不一致问题，但是在运行一段时间后
be transient differences but in the long
所有的日志都会被 leader 修改，直到 leader 确保所有日志是完全相同的
run all the logs will sort of be
modified by the leader until the leader
所有的日志都会被 leader 修改，直到 leader 确保所有日志是完全相同的
insurers are all identical and only then
并且只有在那时候，命令才会被执行
are they executed okay so I think the
嗐！还有 2 个大的关于 raft 的话题需要讨论！
next there's really two big topics to
talk about here for raft one is how
一个是 Leader Election(领导选举)是如何工作的，在 lab2 中需要完成
leader election works which is lab two
另一个是 leader 要如何处理不同的副本日志，尤其是出错之后
and the other is how the leader deals
with the different replicas logs
另一个是 leader 要如何处理不同的副本日志，尤其是出错之后
particularly after failure so first I
所以咱们先来谈谈 leader election
want to talk about leader election
有个要问的问题是，为什么系统需要 leader?
question to ask is how come the system
为什么我们需要 leader?
even has a leader why do we need a
答案之一是，你可以构建一个没有 leader 的系统
leader the part of the answer is you do
not need a leader to build a system like
在一个集群上构建一个共识系统是可能的
this you it is possible to build an
agreement system by which a cluster of
在不指定 leader 的情况下，你可以让日志中的一个序列的日志项达成一致
servers agrees you know the sequence of
entries in a log without having any kind
在不指定 leader 的情况下，你可以让日志中的一个序列的日志项达成一致
of designated leader
事实上，论文中提到了原始的 paxos 系统，它就没有 leader
and indeed the original paxos system
which the paper refers to original Paxos
事实上，论文中提到了原始的 paxos 系统，它就没有 leader
did not have a leader so it's possible
那为什么在 raft 里 leader 是如此重要？
the reason why raft has a leader is
有很多可能的原因
basically that there's probably a lot of
但是，最重要的一个原因是，你能构建更加高效的系统
reasons but one of the foremost reasons
is that you can build a more efficient
因为通常情况下，服务器很少会发生错误
in the common case in which the server's
所以如果有 leader 的话，你就能构建一个更加高效的系统
don't fail it's possible to build a more
efficient system if you have a leader
因为指定了 leader 的话，所有人都知道 leader 是谁
because with a designated leader
everybody knows who the leader is you
每个客户端请求，只要发送一轮消息，就能达成一致
can basically get agreement on requests
that with one round of messages per
在无 leader 的系统中，就需要做更多的事情
request without leader of this systems
have more of the flavor of well you need
首先你需要发送一轮消息为一个临时 leader 达成一致
a first round to kind of agree on a
然后再第二轮中实际发出请求
temporary leader and then a second round
所以这是使用 leader 加速系统的一个可能的 case(案例)
actually send out the requests so it's
probably the case that use of a leader
所以这是使用 leader 加速系统的一个可能的 case(案例)
speeds up the system by a factor two
并且，有了 leader 之后，我们也能很容易的思考接下来的行为
and it also makes it sort of easier to
think about what's going on
raft 会经历一系列的 leader
raft goes through a sequence of leaders and it
它使用 term(任期，单调递增的逻辑时钟)号来标识不同的 leader
uses these term numbers in order to sort
目的是为了和 leader 通信时，避免歧义
of disambiguate which leader we're talking about
其实 follower 并不需要知道 leader 的标识号
it turns out that
followers don't really need to know the
其实 follower 并不需要知道 leader 的标识号
identity of the leader they really just
它只要知道当前的 term 号就行了
need to know what the current term number is
每个 term 至多有一个 leader
each term has at most one
这是一个非常关键的性质
leader that's a critical property you
也不是每个任期内都有 leader 存在
know for every term there might be no
leader during that term or there might
一个任期里可以有一个 leader，也可能没有 leader
be one leader but there cannot be two
在同一个任期里，不可能出现 2 个 leader，每个任期最多只能有 1 个
leaders during the same term every term
has it must most one leader how do the
首先，怎么才能创建一个 leader 出来？
leaders get created in the first place
每一个 raft 服务器都会持有一个选举定时器
every raft server keeps this election
这个定时器超时后，就会去执行一些事情
timer which is just a it's basically
just out of time that it has recorded
这个定时器超时后，就会去执行一些事情
that says well if that time occurs I'm
going to do something and the something
做什么事情呢？如果一个完整的 leader 选举周期到期了
that it does is that if an entire leader
具体的说，如果一个完整的 leader 选举周期到期了
election period expires without the
但是 server （副本，follower)没有收到任何来自当前 leader 的消息
server having heard any message from the
current leader then the server sort of
那么 server 就会假设: 咦，是不是 leader 挂了？
assumes probably that the current leader
然后它就开始发起一次新的选举
is dead and starts an election so we
所以，我们有这样一个选举定时器
have this election timer
如果它到期了，就发起一次选举
and if it expires we start an election
发起一次新的 leader 选举，主要做的事情是先执行 term++
and what it means to start an election
is basically that you increment the term
然后 server 会变成 candidate 状态
the the candidate the server that's
decided it's going to be a candidate and
并且强制发起新一轮选举
sort of force a new election first
先增加 term 的原因是，它自己想成为新的 leader
increments this term because it wants
them to be a new leader namely itself
你知道，同一个任期不允许超过一个 leader
and you know leader a term can't have
more than one leader so we got to start
所以我们需要从一个新的 term 开始，以选举出新的 leader
a new term in order to have a new leader
然后，它会发送 RequestVotes RPC 给其它所有的 server
and then it sends out these RequestVotes RPCs
I'm going to send
然后，它会发送 RequestVotes RPC 给其它所有的 server
out a full round of request votes and
可能只需要发送 N-1 条 RequestVotes 出去
you may only have to send out n minus
one requests votes because one of the
因为这其中有一条规则是，在选举过程中，candidate 总是先给它自己投一票
rules is that a new candidate always
votes for itself in the election so one
需要注意的一点是
thing to note about this is that it's
如果 leader 没有产生错误，那就不会产生选举
not quite the case that if the leader
，如果 leader 没有产生错误，那就不会产生选举
didn't fail we won't have an election
假设其它所有的 server 都在正常运行
但是如果 leader 出错了，那么我们才会进行选举
but if the leader does fail then we will
假设其它所有的 server 都在正常运行
但是如果 leader 出错了，那么我们才会进行选举
have election an election assuming any
假设其它所有的 server 都在正常运行
但是如果 leader 出错了，那么我们才会进行选举
other server is up because some day the
因为这时其它 server 的选举定时器会到期
other servers election timers go will go
但是 leader 一直安然无恙的话，也可能会很不幸的发起选举
off but as leader didn't fail we might
still unfortunately get an election so
比如网络太慢，或者心跳包丢失或是别的什么原因
if the network is slow or drops a few
heartbeats or something we may end up
最终还是会会导致选举定时器超时
having election timers go off and even
即使你有一个十分完美的 leader
though there was a perfectly good leader
然而也可能会有新选举产生
we may nevertheless have a new election
所以当我们考虑正确性的时候，需要要记住这一点
so we have to sort of keep that in mind
we're thinking about the
term 是做什么用的呢？
correctness and what that in term means
如果有新的选举发起，很容易想到的一个场景是
is that if there's a new election it
could easily be the case that the old
旧的 leader 仍然在运行，并且它仍然认为它自己是 leader
leader is still hanging around and still
thinks it's the leader like if there's a
比如网络产生分区的时候，旧的 leader 仍然存活
network partition for example and the
old leader is still alive and well in a
并且处在一个只包含不到一半 server 的分区中
minority partition the majority
那么超过一半 server 的分区可能会发起选举
partition may run an election and indeed
并且也能成功选出一个新的 leader
a successful election and choose a new
它完全不知道旧的 leader 的存在
leader all totally unknown to the
所以我也们会担心，比如旧的 leader 会干啥
previous leader so we also have to worry
about you know what's that previous
因为它也不知道发生了新的 leader 选举
leader gonna do since it does not know
there was a new election yes
问题是：是否存在这种病态的 case，例如一个只能单向通信的网络
okay so the question is are there can
there be pathological cases in which for
问题是：是否存在这种病态的 case，例如一个只能单向通信的网络
example one-way network communication
在这种情况下，系统还能正常运行下去吗
can prevent the system from making
我认为答案是 yes
progress I believe the answer is yes
比如说，如果当前 leader，它的网络出现某种单向故障
certainly so for example if the current
leader if its network somehow half fails
当前 leader 可以把心跳发送出去
in a way the current leader can send out
heartbeats
但是无法接收任何客户端请求
but can't receive any client requests
因为网络的出口没问题，心跳包全都被发送出去了
then the heartbeats that it sends out
which are delivered because it's
因为网络的出口没问题，心跳包全都被发送出去了
outgoing network connection works its
它的心跳会压制住其它 server 发起选举
outgoing heartbeats will suppress any
other server from starting an election
但是，网络入口却出了故障
but the fact that it's incoming Network
why or apparently is broken will prevent
这就导致它无法接收到任何客户端的命令
it from hearing and executing any client
这也确实是 raft 不能解决所有疯狂的网络问题案例
commands it's absolutely the case that
raft is not proof against all sort of
这也确实是 raft 不能解决所有疯狂的网络问题案例
all crazy Network problems that can come
我觉得这样应该可以解决问题
up I believe the ones I've thought about
I believe are fixable in the sense that
从某种意义上来说，你可以做一个双向的心跳功能
the we could solve this one by having a
sort of requiring a two-way heartbeat in
比如 leader 发送出心跳包后，follwer 被要求回应心跳包
which if the leader sends out heartbeats
but you know there were in which
比如 leader 发送出心跳包后，follwer 被要求回应心跳包
followers are required to reply in some
way to heartbeats I guess they are
我猜在 apply 这一步，这些回应是需要的
already required to apply if the leader
如果 leader 没有看见对心跳的回应
stop seeing replies to its heartbeats
过一段很长一段时间后，才看见回应
then after some amount of time and which
see the replies the leader decides
leader 就会自己决定下台
to step down I feel like that specific
我感觉这个特殊的 issue 是可以被修复的
issue can be fixed and many others can
当然其它的问题也是能被解决的
too but I but you know you're absolutely
不过我觉得你的问题也完全是正确的
right that very strange things can
网络协议没有准备就绪的话，这种奇怪的问题是可能会发生的
happen to networks including some that
the protocol is not prepared for
okay，leader 选举 就是这些
okay so we got these leader elections we
我们需要确保一个 term 至多只有一个 leader
need to ensure that there is at most at
most one leader per term
raft 如何做呢？对于一个 term 来说
how does raft do that well raft requires
raft 要求 candidate 得到半数以上 server 的投票
in order to be elected for a term Raft
requires a candidate to get yes votes
raft 要求 candidate 得到半数以上 server 的 yes 投票
from a majority of the server's the
每个 server 在一个 term 中只能投一票 yes
servers and each server will only cast
one yes vote per term so in any given
所以在任何一个 term 中，只能为一个 candidate 投一票
term you know it basically means that in
any given term either votes only once
所以在任何一个 term 中，只能为一个 candidate 投一票
for only one candidate you can't have
这样就不可能同时有 2 个 candidate 获得半数以上的选票
two candidates both get a majority of
因为每个只能投一次票
votes because everybody votes only once
所以 majority 规则保证了至多只有一个 candidate 胜出
so the majorities majority rule causes
there to be at most one winning
也以我们也能保证在一个 term 中至多只有一个 candidate 被选出
candidate and so then we get at most one
candidate elected per term
另外，majority 规则的关键含义是
and in addition critically the majority
即使有一些 server 宕机了，也能选举成功
rule means that you can get elected even
if some servers have crashed right if a
如果有不到一半的 server 宕机了，不可用了，网络故障了
minority of servers are crashed aren't
available and network problems we can
我们仍然能选出一个 leader
still elect a leader if more than half a
如果有超过一半宕机，不可用或处于其它的分区中
crash or not available or in another
那么整个系统就坐那不动了（停止）
partition or something then actually the
system will just sit there trying again
它会一遍又一遍的发起 leader 选举，但是却又永远选不出 leader
and again to elect a leader and never
因为存活的机器不超过一半，事实上也不能选出 leader
elect one if it cannot in fact they're
not a majority of live servers if an
如果选举成功，并且每个节点都知道了这件事，那么一切安好
election succeeds everybody would be
great if everybody learned about it I
我们需要问一下自己，假设没有 server 宕机
mean need to ask ourselves how do all
所有的 server 是如何知道哪个 server 赢得了选举？
the parties learn learn what happened
the server that wins an election
所有的 server 是如何知道哪个 server 赢得了选举？
assuming it doesn't crash the server
赢得选举的 server 也确实看到了半数以上对它的投票
that wins election will actually see a
赢得选举的 server 也确实看到了半数以上其它 server 对它的投票
majority or positive votes for its
request vote from a majority of the
发起选举的 candidate 赢得了投票
other servers so the candidates running
the election that wins it the candidates
发起选举的 candidate 赢得了投票
that wins the election will actually
它自己当然很清楚自己赢得了半数以上的选票
know directly uh I got a majority of
但是其它的 server 不知道呀
votes but nobody else directly knows who
the winner was or whether anybody one so
所以取胜的 candidate 需要通知其它 server
the way that the candidate informs other
也就是使用心跳
servers is that heartbeat the rules and
图 2 中说，如果你赢得了选举
figure 2 say oh if you win an
就应该立刻发送 AppendEntries 到其它 server
election your immediately required to
send out AppendEntries
就应该立刻发送 AppendEntries 到其它 server
to all the other servers now the
AppendEntries 并不直接会包含这个信息
append entries that heartbeat append
哦，我赢得了选票，我是 term 23 的 leader
entries doesn't explicitly say I won the
election you know I'm a leader for term
这里有一点微妙的地方
23 it's a little more subtle than that
除了 leader，其它人是不允许发送 AppendEntries 消息的
the the way the information is
communicated is that no one is allowed
除了 leader，其它人是不允许发送 AppendEntries 消息的
to send out an append entries unless
they're a leader for that term so the
所以事实上是这样，我是一个 server
fact that I I'm a you know I'm a server
我看到了在 term 19 的那次选举
and I saw oh there's an election for
过了一会儿，我leader 发送了一条 term 为 19 的 AppendEntires
term 19 and then by-and-by I sent an
过了一会儿，leader 发送了一条 term 为 19 的 AppendEntires
append entries whose term is 19 that
然后我收到了，我就知道有人赢得了这次选举，虽然我不清楚是谁赢得了选举
tells me that somebody I don't know who
but somebody won the election so that's
所以这就是其它 server 如何得知有人赢得选举的
how the other servers knows they were
它们接收到那个 term 的 AppendEntries 消息
receiving append entries for that term
那条 AppendEntries 消息，也会重置每个 server 的选举定时器
and that append entries also has the
effect of resetting everybody's election
只要 leader 存活，那就会发送心跳消息，或者说是 AppendEntries
time timer so as long as the leader is
up and it sends out heartbeat messages
只要 leader 存活，那就会发送心跳消息，或者说是 AppendEntries
or append entries at least you know at
每次 server 收到了一条 AppendEntries
the rate that's supposed to every time a
server receives an append entries it'll
它就会重置它的选举定时器
reset its selection timer and sort of
压制任何人变成为 candidate
suppress anybody from being a new
只要一切运作正常，这些重复的心跳就能阻止新的选举产生
candidate so as long as everything's
functioning the repeated heartbeats will
只要一切运作正常，这些重复的心跳就能阻止新的选举产生
prevent any further elections of course
当然了，如果有网络故障，或是丢失消息
it the network fails or packets are
仍然会导致新的选举被发起
dropped there may nevertheless be an
若一切安好，那就不太可能发起新的选举
election but if all goes well we're sort
of unlikely to get an election this
这个方案可能会失效
scheme could fail in the sense that it
对于同一个 term 来说，不会选出 2 个 leader 出来
can't fail in the sense of electing two
leaders for a term but it can fail in the
但可能会一个 leader 都选不出来，这时候就失败了
sense of electing zero leaders for a
有太多种情况会导致失败
term that's sort of many way it may
比如有太多的服务器宕机或不可用，网络连接故障
fail is that if too many servers are
dead or unavailable or a bad network
所以这个时候，你就没办法组合出 majoirity 出来
connection so if you can't assemble a
因此也就无法选出任何 leader 出来，啥也不会发生
majority you can't be elected nothing
还有一些更有趣的选举失败的方式
happens the more interesting way in
which an election can fail is if
所有人都是健在的，也没有网络丢包
everybody's up you know there's no
failures no packets are dropped but two
但是同时有 2 个 leaders(可能是口误，应该是2个 follower)
几乎在同一时刻成为了 candidate
leaders become candidate close together
他们之间将会瓜分选票，或者说是有 3 个人一起瓜分吧
enough in time that they split the vote
between them or say three leaders
假设我们有 3 个 leader
so supposing we have three leaders
假设我们的系统中有 3 个副本
supposing we have a three replica system
他们 3 个人的选举定时器几乎在同一时刻到期，每个人都先给自己投一票
all their election timers go off at the
same time every server votes for itself
接下来，他们每个人又会收到其它 server 的选票请求
and then when each of them receives a
request vote from another server well
好了，因为它自己已经把票投给了自己，所以它就会回复 no.
it's already cast its vote for itself
这样的结果就是 3 个服务器各自有一张选票
and so it says no so that means that it
all three of the servers each get
没有一个人的选票超过半数，所以也就没有 leader 被选出
one vote each nobody gets a majority and
nobody's elected so then their election
然后他们的选举定时器会再一次超时
timers will go off again because the
因为只有在收到 AppendEntires 时选举定时器才会被重置
election timers only reset if it gets
但是没有 leader 被选出来，因此也就没有 AppendEntries 消息
an append entries but there's no leader
so no append entries they'll all have
他们的选举定时器会再一次超时
their election timers go off again and
如果很不幸的是又在同一时刻超时
if we're unlucky
they'll all go off at the same time
于是他们又会自己给自己投票
they'll all vote for themselves nobody
然后又没有人拿到半数以上的选票
will get a majority so so clearly I'm
我相信你们都已经注意到这一点了
sure you're all aware at this point
这个故事还有更多的后续
there's more to this story and the way
raft 让这种瓜分选票的概率变的非常低，但是也不是不可能发生
Raft makes this possibility of split
votes unlikely but not impossible
raft 通过随机化选举定时器的超时时间
is by randomizing these election timers
怎么去想这件事呢？
so the way to think of it and the
怎么去思考随机化呢？
randomization the way to think of it is
假设有一条时间线
that supposing you have some time line
我打算在某些位置上画一些事件
I'm gonna draw events on there's some
在这里，是每个人收到最后一次 AppendEntries 的时间
point at which everybody received the
last append entries right and then maybe
然后我们假设发送最后一个心跳的服务器宕机了
the server died let's just assume the
server send out a last heartbeat and
所有 follower 会在这个位置重置他们的选举定时器
then died well all of the followers have
this we set their election timers when
因为他们可能会在同时收到这条 AppendEntries
they received at the same time because
they probably all receive this append
因为他们可能会在同时收到这条 AppendEntries
enters at the same time they all reset
然后在这个位置重置选举定时器
their election timers for some point in
在未来的某个时间点这些定时器会到期
the future the future but they chose
它们他们会选择一个随机的时间来设定这个定时器
different random times in the future
which then we're gonna go off
假设 leader S1 宕机了
so it's suppose the dead leader server
所以现在 S2 和 S2 会在这里设置他们选举定时器
one so now server two and server 3 at
this point set their election timers for
并未来的某个时刻随机选一个位置表示到期时间
a random point in the future let's say
假设 S2 设定在这个位置表示到期
server 2 set there I like some timer to
S3 选择在这个位置到期
go off here and server 3 set its
election timer to go off there and the
这幅图的一个关键点是假设他们选择了一个不同的随机数字
crucial point about this picture is that
assuming they picked different random
它是第一个，它是第二个
numbers one of them is first and the
other one is second right that's what's
这里将会发生什么？
going on here and the one that's first
假设这里之间的间隙足够长
assuming
this gap is big enough the one that's
第一个位置选举定时器会在另一个之前到期
first it's election time will go off
first before the other ones election
如果我们不会那么不走运
timer and if we were not
unlucky
那么这里就有足够长的时间发送一轮投票，并能得到每个人的回复
it'll have time to send out a full round
of vote requests and get answers from
那么这里就有足够长的时间发送一轮投票，并能得到每个人的回复
everybody who everybody's alive before
这些都会在第二个选举定时器到期之前发生
the second election timer goes off from
所以，大家明白随机化是怎么去同步化操作的了吗？
any other server so does everybody see
how the randomization desynchronizes
所以不幸的是，给这些定时器设定内容需要一点点艺术
these candidates unfortunately there's a
bit of art in setting the contents
所以不幸的是，给这些定时器设定内容需要一点点艺术
constants for these election timers
你可能需要满足一些条件
there's some sort of competing
requirements you might want to fulfill
典型的条件之一是
so one obvious requirement is that the
定时器的超时时间至少要和 2 次心跳间隔的时间一样长
election timer has to be at least as
long as the expected interval between
定时器的超时时间至少要和 2 次心跳间隔的时间一样长
heartbeats
这一点很明显
you know this is pretty obvious that the
leader 每隔几百毫秒发送一次心跳
leader sends out heartbeats every
每隔几百毫秒发送一次心跳
hundred milliseconds you better make
你最好得确保在这之间不会有人的选举定时器超时
sure there's no point in having the
election time or anybody's election time
你最好得确保在这之间不会有人的选举定时器超时
or ever go off for 100
如果它在最低的限制之前超时
milliseconds because then it will go off
before the lower limit is certainly the
最低的限制就是心跳之间的间隔
lower limit is one heartbeat interval in
因为网络可能会丢弃数据包
fact because the network may drop
所以你可能会想着把这个最小的选举超时时间设定为心跳间隔时间的 2 倍
packets you probably want to have the
minimum election timer value be a couple
所以你可能会想着把这个最小的选举超时时间设定为心跳间隔时间的 2 倍
of times the heartbeat interval so 400
所以你可以设置成 400ms，也可能设置一个最短的选举时间
millisecond heartbeats you probably want
to have the very shortest possible
又或是设置成心跳间隔时间的 3 倍，比如 300ms
election time or be you know say 300
milliseconds you know three times the
这里是最小的心跳时间间隔
heartbeat interval so that's the sort of
minimum is the heart heartbeat so this
这里是最小的心跳时间间隔
frequent you want the minimum to be you
这里是心跳间隔的 2 倍
know a couple of times that or here so
最大值在哪里呢
what about the maximum you know you're
你可以假定使用一个均匀分布生成某个范围的随机值
gonna presumably randomize uniformly
over some range of times you know where
我们应该设置一个最大值在这儿，这里随机出的最大时间
should we set the kind of maximum time
that we're randomizing over there's a
在真实系统中，这里有 2 点考虑
couple of considerations here in a real
最大时间会影响系统有多快能从故障中恢复
system you know this maximum time effect
how quickly the system can recover from
因为，假设服务器从这个位置开始出故障
failure because remember from the time
at which the server fails until the
那么在选举定时器超时之前，整体系统都处于不可用状态
first election timer goes off the whole
system is frozen there's no leader you
此时没有任何 leader，客户端发的所有请求都会被丢弃
know the clients requests are being
thrown away because there's no leader
而且我们也没有重新指定一个新的 leader 出来
and we're not assigning a new leader
即使你知道其它的这些 server 是健康的
even though you know presumably these
other servers are up so the be away
所以我们选的最大值越靠后，延迟就越长
choose this maximum the longer delay
在系统恢复前，对客户端的影响就越长
we're imposing on clients before
你知道，关于这一点，取决于你想要多高的性能
recovery occurs you know whether that's
important depends on sort of how high
你知道，关于这一点，取决于你想要多高的性能、故障发生的频率
performance we need this to be and how
often we think there will be failures
一年只发生一次故障的话，鬼才会去关心这个问题
failures happen once a year then who cares
如果故障发生很频率的话
we're expecting failures frequently we
那我们就需要去关心到底要设置的多长的时间，让故障恢复
may care very much how long it takes to
所以这是第一个我们需要考虑的问题
recover okay so that's one consideration
另一个要考虑的事情是这里这个间隔
the other consideration is that this gap
S1 超时，到 S2 超时这个时间间隔
that is the expected gap in time between
the first time are going off and the
S1 超时，到 S2 超时这个时间间隔
second timer going off this gap really
这个间隔非常有用，而且它要足够的长
in order to be useful has to be longer
足够让 candidate 能收到其它人的投票
than the time it takes for the candidate
to assemble votes from everybody that is
它要比一次 RPC 请求到响应的来回时间要长一些
longer than the expected round-trip time
the amount of time it takes to send an
它要比一次 RPC 请求到响应的来回时间要长一些
RPC and get the response and so maybe it
比如发送一次 RPC 到收到所有其它 server 响应需要 10ms
takes 10 milliseconds to send an RPC and
get a response a response from all the
在这种情况下，我们设置的最大值，至少要让这个间隔大于 10ms
other servers and if that's the case we
need to make maximum at least long
在这种情况下，我们设置的最大值，至少要让这个间隔大于 10ms
enough that there's pretty likely to be
也就是最小的这个随机数到下一个最小的随机数之间的差值能大于 10ms
10 milliseconds difference between the
smallest random number and the next
也就是最小的这个随机数到下一个最小的随机数之间的差值能大于 10ms
smallest random number
对你们来说，那些测试代码可能会让你们感觉到痛苦
and for you the test code will get upset
如果经过若干秒后你的 leader 都未能从故障中恢复
if you if you don't recover from a
leader failure in a couple seconds and
那你就需要考虑一下调优这个最大值，把它设置的小一点
so just pragmatically you need to tune
this maximum down so that it's highly
只要它能让你在几秒内完成 leader 选举就行
likely that you'll be able to complete a
leader election within a few seconds but
这就算是一个不那么紧的约束
that's not a very tight constraint any
关于选举时间大家还有问题吗？
questions about the election time outs
还有一个不起眼的问题是
one tiny point is that you want to
每次你都应该选择一个新的随机超时时间
choose new random time outs every time
是的，每次都需要随机生成一个
there's every time you every time I note
每次你都需要重新设定这个定时器
sets it to like me sets its election
你不要在服务器启动的时候，随机生成一个数字重复使用它
timer that is don't choose a random
number when the server is first created
你不要在服务器启动的时候，随机生成一个数字重复使用它
and then we use that same number over
and over again because you make an
如果你这样做，你的服务器可能会产生一些不良行为
unlucky choice that is you choose this
one server happens by ill chance to
比如会导致每次选举的选票都被瓜分掉，直到永远
choose the same random number as another
server that means that you're gonna have
比如会导致每次选举的选票都被瓜分掉，直到永远
split votes over and over again forever
这就是为什么你需要每次都生成一个新的随机数来设定选举超时时间
that's why you want to almost certainly
choose a different a new fresh random
这就是为什么你需要每次都生成一个新的随机数来设定选举超时时间
number for the election time out value
every time you reset the timer all right
好，最后一个关于 leader 选举的问题
so the final issue about leader election
假设我们在这样一种情形
suppose we are in this situation where
旧的 leader 处于一个网络分区中，比如网线断了
the old leaders partition you know the
network cable is broken and the old
旧 leader 以及 2 个客户端
leader is sort of out there with a
还有不越过半数的 server 在这个分区中
couple clients and a minority of servers
另一半的网络分区中有超过半数的 server
and there's a majority in the other half
在这个超过半数 server 的分区中又选举出了一个新的 leader
of the network and the majority of the
new half of the network elects a new
那旧的 leader 会怎么样？
leader what about the old leader why why
为什么旧的 leader 不会导致错误的行为
won't the old leader cause incorrect execution
是的，有 2 个潜在的问题
yes to two potential problems one is or
其中一个问题是
one some non problem is that if there's
如果有一个 leader 处于一个不超过半数 server 的分区中
a leader off in another partition and it
doesn't have a majority then the next
客户端发送给它请求后，你知道这个 leader 处在少数派的分区中
time a client sends it a request that
that leader that you know in a partition
客户端发送给它请求后，你知道这个 leader 处在少数派的分区中
with a minority yeah it'll send out
它会发送 AppendEntries，但是因为在少数派中
append entries but because it's in the
所以它无法得到半数以上 server（包括自己） 的回应
minority partition it won't be able to
get responses back from a majority of
所以它无法得到半数以上 server（包括自己） 的回应
the server's including itself and so it
所以它永远都不会把客户端请求的操作进行提交
will never commit the operation it will
也永远不会去执行它
never execute it
它永远也不会去响应客户端说它执行完了这条命令
it'll never respond to the client saying
that it executed it either and so that
这意思是说如果一个旧的 server(leader)
means that yeah an old server often a
经常处于不同的分区中
different partition people many clients
许多客户可能发送的请求都无法得到响应
may send a request but they'll never get
所以客户端也不会误以为旧的 server 执行过任何命令
responses so no client will be fooled
into thinking that that old server
所以客户端也不会误以为旧的 server 执行过任何命令
executed anything for it the other sort
另一个更加 tricky（巧合) 的问题，待会儿咱们再说
of more tricky issue which actually I'll
talk about in a few minutes is the
是关于 server 在发送 AppendEntries 到一部分 server 后宕机的可能性
possibility that before server fails it
sends out append entries to a subset of
是关于 server 在发送 AppendEntries 到一部分 server 后宕机的可能性
the servers and then crashes before
在做 commit 决策之前，它就宕机了
making a commit decision and as a very
这是一个很有趣的问题，我可能得花 45 分钟来讨论它
interesting question which I'll probably
spend a good 45 minutes talking about
我们先回到刚刚话题
and so actually before I turn to the
关于 leader 选举，大家还有其它问题吗？
back topic in general any more questions
about in leader election okay
好，关于 log 中的内容是什么样的
okay so how about the contents of the
在前一个 leader 挂掉之后，如何进行新一轮 leader 选举
logs and how in particular how a newly
elected leader possibly picking up the
在前一个 leader 挂掉之后，如何进行新一轮 leader 选举
pieces after an awkward crash of the
log 产生分叉的话，如何进行 leader 选举
previous leader how does a newly elected
leader sort out the possibly divergent
log 产生分叉的话，如何进行 leader 选举
logs on the different replicas in order
来恢复系统中的一致性的状态
to restore sort of consistent state in
the system all right so the first
关于第一个问题，你能想到什么
question is what can think this is this
这是一个完整的话题
whole topic it's really only interesting
关于 server 宕机后我们唯一比较感兴趣的事情
after a server crashes right if the
如果 server 一直很健康，并且一切事情进展顺利
server stays up then relatively few
things can go wrong if we have a server
我们拥有一个健康的 server 和超过半数的机器
that's up and has a majority you know
在一段时间内他们都是健康的
during the period of time when it's up
and has a majority it just tells the
leader 只要通知 follwer 日志应该是什么样的就行
followers what the logs should look like
follwer 是不允许反对 leader 的
and the followers are not allowed to
如果它们基本上都是保持最新的状态的
那么只需要服从 leader，只要按照图 2 中的规则做事就行
disagree they're required to accept they
如果它们基本上都是保持最新的状态的
那么只需要服从 leader，只要按照图 2 中的规则做事就行
just do by the rules of figure two if
如果它们基本上都是保持最新的状态的
那么只需要服从 leader，只要按照图 2 中的规则做事就行
they've been more or less keeping up you
它们就只是简单的使用 leader 发给他们的 AppendEntires
know they just take whatever the leader
sends them AppendEntries appended
追加到自己的日志上，并提交这些消息，然后执行
to the log and obey commit messages and
这几乎不会发生什么错误
execute there's hardly anything to go
在 raft 中，有些事情会导致故障
wrong the things that go wrong in raft
比如当一个旧的 leader 在发送消息的中途宕机了
go wrong when a the old leader crashes
sort of midway through you know sending
又或者是刚刚新选举的 leader 宕机了
out messages or a new leader crashes you
又或者是刚刚新选举的 leader，啥了没干就宕机了
know sort of just after it's been
elected but before it's done anything
所以我们感兴趣的是，这经过一连串的 crase 后，log 长啥样？
very useful so one thing we're very
interested in is what can the logs look
所以我们感兴趣的是，这经过一连串的 crase 后，log 长啥样？
like after some sequence of crashes okay
来，咱们讲个例子，假设我们有 3 台服务器
so here's an example supposing we have
我准备画一些图，等会我们会看到很多情况
three servers and the way I'm gonna draw
out these diagrams because we're gonna
我准备画一些图，等会我们会看到很多情况
be looking a lot at a lot of sort of
不同情况下的 log 都是什么样的
situations where the logs look like this
我们需要推演各种可能性下会发生什么
and we're gonna be wondering is that
possible and what happens if they do
我会在这里使用一些记号表示日志项
look like that so my notation is going
to be I'm gonna write out log entries
对于每个 server，相同位置的槽都是对齐的
for each of the servers sort of aligned
to indicate slots corresponding slots in
这里这个数字表示的是 term 号，不是客户端命令
the log and the values I'm going to
write here are the term numbers rather than
这里这个数字表示的是 term 号，不是客户端命令
client operations I'm going to you know
这里是槽 1，这里这是槽 2
this is slot one this is slot two
所有的服务器在 1 号槽上都看到了来自 term 3 的命令
everybody saw a command from term three
S2 和 S3 看到了来自 term 3 的命令
in slot 1 and server 2 server 3
saw command from also term three and the
而在 2 号槽上，S1 什么也没有
second slot the server one has nothing
所以，这个问题，也是咱们的第一个问题，它是如何发生的？
there at all and so question for this
like the very first question is can this
这种情况会发生吗？怎么发生的？
arrive could this setup arise and how
是的
yes
S3 可能是 leader
so you know maybe server 3 was the
我就把你刚刚说的话重复一下
leader for just repeating what you said
S3 可能是 term 3 的 leader
maybe server 3 is the leader for term 3
它收到了一条命令，然后发给每个人
he got a command that sent out to
然后每个收到它追加到自己的 log 中
everybody everybody received and apended
接下来 S3 又收到了一条来自客户端的请求
at the log and then I got a server 3 got
a second request from a client and maybe
它可能发它发送给了所有的 server
it sent it to all three servers but the
但是这条消息在发送给 S1 时丢失了，也可能是 S1 宕机了
message got lost on the way to server
one or maybe server was down at the time
leader 在发送 AppendEntires 之前
or something and so only server two the
总是能追加新的命令到自己的 log 中的
leader always append new commands to its
log before it sends out append entries
AppendEntires RPC 仅仅被  S2 收到
and maybe the append entry RPC only got
所以在这种情况下
to server 2 so this situation you know
这只是一种很简单的日志不一致的情况
it's like the simplest situation in which
actually the logs are not different and
我们知道它可能会怎么样发生
we know how it could possibly arise and
所以如果作为 leader 的 S3 宕机了
so if server 3 which is a leadership
那么现在你就必须得再选一个新的 server
crash now you know the next server
they're gonna need to make sure server 1
那么现在你就必须得再选一个新的 server
well first of all if server 3 crashes or
we'll be at an election and some of the
会有某个 leader 被选出来
leader is chosen you know two things
有 2 件事件一定会发生
have to happen the new leader has got to
新的 leader 需要能识别出这条命令是提交过的
recognize that this command could have
它也不允许丢弃这条日志
committed it's not allowed to throw it away
另外它需要保证 S1 填充此处的空白
and it needs to make sure server one
fills in this blank here with indeed
以和别人在同样的位置保持一致
this very same command that everybody
else had in that slot all right so after
所以在某个 server 宕机后
a crash somebody you know server 3
所以另一种可能出现此情况的方式是
suppose another way this can come up is
S3 在给 S2 发送 AppendEntries 后，但是在给 S1 发送前宕机了
server 3 might have sent out the append
entries the server 2 but then crashed
S3 在给 S2 发送 AppendEntries 后，但是在给 S1 发送前宕机了
before sending the append entries to server 3（口误，应该是 S1）
所以，如果你你选了一个新的 leader 出来
so if were you know electing a
在发送消息之前就宕机了，这就导致了这种情况
new leader it could because we got a
crash before the message was sent
我们再考虑另一种情况，仍然有 3 个 server
here's another scenario to think about
three servers again now I mean a number
日志里有一些槽，假设它们编号分别是 10, 11, 12, 13
the slots in the log and so we can refer
to them got slot 10 11 12 13
这里设置相同的值，除了 12 号槽
again it's same setup except now we have
我们假设 S2 在 term 4 有一条命令
in slot 12 we have server 2 as a
而 S3 在 term 5 时有一条命令
command from term 4 and server 3 has a
term command from term 5
呃，在我们分析这个情形前，我们先思考一下
so you know before we analyze these to
这种情况会发生吗？
figure out what would happen and what
如果 server 看到这种情况，应该要怎么做？
would a server do if it saw this we need
to ask could this even occur because
如果出现了这种情况的话，有时候大家的回答是
sometimes the answer to the question oh
Oh! 上帝，这发生了什么？
jeez what would happen if this
configuration arose sometimes the answer
有时候的答案是，它不可能出现，所以我们也不用担心这个问题
is it cannot arise so we do not have to
所以我们的问题是，这种情况会发生吗？如果会的话，怎么才能出现？
worry about it the question is could
this arise and how
不错
all right so any
(回答问题)
太棒了
yeah
我简单说一下，这种情况是可能出现的
in brief we know this configuration can
这里变成 4 和 5 的方式可以是这样的
arise and so the way we can then get the
four and a five here is let's suppose in
我们假设开始进行一次 leader 选举
the next leader election server twos
S2 成为了 term 4 的 leader
elected leader now for term 4 its
这时候客户端发起一次请求，S2 追加了一条日志后 crash 掉
selected leader because a request from a
client it appends it to its own log and
所以这里变成了 4
crashes so now we have this right we
因为 leader S2 刚刚 crash 了
need a new election because the leader
现在我们需要进行一次新的选举
just crashed now in this election and
现在我们需要问一下自己，谁可以被选为 leader
then so now we have to ask whether who
我们必须回过头好好想想，什么样的 server 可以被选出来
could be elected or we have to give him
back of our heads oh gosh what could be
这里 S3 可以被选为 leader
elected so we're gonna claim server
three could be elected the reason why I
为什么我能选它是因为它只要获得了大多数的选票就行
could be elected is because it only
needs request vote responses from
这里 majority 是 S1 和 S3
majority that majority is server one and
因为 S1 和 S3 的 log 并没什么冲突
server three you know there's no no
problem no conflict between these two
所以 S3 可以被选为 term 5 的 leader
logs so server three can be elected for
然后 S3 收到了客户端的请求，追加了一条日志后就 crash
term five get a request from a client
append it to its own log and crash and
这就是形成这种情况的方式
that's how you get this this
你需要反复思考这些事情，并达到理解的程度
configuration so you know you need to be
able to to work through these things in
并能够回答这个问题：是的，这种情况可以发生
order to get to the stage of saying yes
因此 raft 必须为此做一些明智的事情
this could happen and therefore raft
而不是因为有些事不能发生，你就说不会发生这种情况
must do something sensible as opposed to
it cannot happen because some things
而不是因为有些事不能发生，你就说不会发生这种情况
can't happen
好，现在我们已经知道这种情况发生的原因
all right so so what can happen now we
know this can occur so hopefully we can
我们要让自己信服，raft 确实是做了一些明智的事情
convince ourselves that raft actually
does something sensible now as for the
对于这些事情，在讨论 raft 实际做了什么之前
range of things before we talk about
what raft would actually would actually
我们需要对什么样的结果是可接受的要有一定的认知
do we need to have some sense of what
would be an acceptable outcome right and
请认真看这里，我们知道 10 号槽里的命令，在所有副本上都有
just eyeballing this we know that the
command in slot 10 since it's known by
请认真看这里，我们知道 10 号槽里的命令，在所有副本上都有
all all the replicas it could have been
它可能是会被提交的，所以我们不能丢弃它
committed so we cannot throw it away
类似的，11 号槽里的命令，因为它被复制到了半数以上节点
similarly the command in slot 11 since
it's in a majority of the replicas it
它也是有可能被提交的，所以不能丢弃
could for all we know have been
committed so we can't throw it away the
在 12 号槽中，这里面的命令都不可能被提交
command in slot 12 however neither of
them could possibly have been committed
所以我们有权利……我们不知道实际上要怎么做
so we're entitled we don't know haven't
但是 raft 是有权利把它丢弃掉的
we'll actually do but raft is entitled
但是 raft 是有权利把它(12 号槽)丢弃掉的
to drop both of these even though it is
即便它没有权利丢弃 10 或 11 号槽的命令
not entitled to drop it and either of
the commands in a 10 or 11
这是有权利丢弃的，但这不是必须要把 2 个都丢弃
this is entitled dropped it's not
required to drop either one of them but
我意思是它必须丢弃其中一个，至少是一个
I mean oh it certainly must drop one at
因为你必须要让 log 尾部的内容保持完全一致
least one because you have to have
identical log contents in the end
这是可能被提交的
this could have been committed it the we
通过看 log 是无法判断的
can't tell by looking at the logs
严格的说，我们无法判断 leader 在 crash 前 log 提交到哪个位置
exactly how far the leader got before
一种可能性是，对于这条命令，又甚至是这条命令
crashing so one possibility is that for
this command or even this command one
leader 发送带有新命令的 Append 消息后，立即 crash 了
possibility is that leaders send out the
append messages with a new command and
leader 发送带有新命令的 Append 消息后，立即 crash 了
then immediately crashed so it never got
所以它就永远无法收到响应，因为它 crash 了
any response back because it crashed so
因此旧的 leader 并不知道它是否已经被提交
the old leader did not know if it was
如果它没有收到响应，这也意味着它没有去执行它
committed and if it didn't get a
response back that means it didn't
它也不会发送增加 commit index 的消息
execute it and it didn't send out but
you know it didn't send out that
它也不会发送增加 commit index 的消息
incremented commit index and so maybe
所以，副本也不会去执行这条命令
the replicas didn't execute it either so
所以实际上可能这个位置是没有提交的
it's actually possible that this wasn't
committed so even though raft doesn't
所以尽管 raft 不知道，对于 raft，它也是合法的
know it could be legal for raft
如果 raft 知道更多的事情话，丢弃这条日志可能是合法的
if raft knew more than it does know it
might be legal to drop this log entry
因为它可能没被提交
because it might not have been committed
但是，根据这些证据，你也没有任何方式去反驳它已被提交
but because on the evidence there's no
way to disprove it was committed based
它可能被提交，但是 raft 无法去证明它
on this evidence it could have been
committed and raft can't prove it wasn't
所以 raft 只能当作它被提交
so it must treat it as committed because
因为 leader 也可能在收到 AppendEntries 的响应之后
并且回复了客户端之后 crash 掉
the leader might have received it might
因为 leader 也可能在收到 AppendEntries 的响应之后
并且回复了客户端之后 crash 掉
have crashed just after receiving the
因为 leader 也可能在收到 AppendEntries 的响应之后
并且回复了客户端之后 crash 掉
append entry replies and replying to the
所以看到这种情形，我们不能排除掉这种可能性
client so just looking at this we can't
rule out the possibility that either
即 leader 回复了客户端之后（crash）
possibility that the leader responded to
在这种情况下，我们不能丢弃这条日志
the client in which case we cannot throw
因为客户端知道它请求成功了
away this entry because a client knows
又或是另一种可能，leader 可能什么也没做过
about it or the possibility the leader
是的，我们不得不假设它是被提交过的
never did and yeah we could you know if
we have to assume that it was committed
嗯呢
yeah
不是，没有。我意思是在这种情况下
no there's no. I mean in this situation maybe
服务器可能会在收到响应之前 crash 掉
the server crash before getting the response
好啦，咱们周四见，拜拜！
it's alright well let's continue this on Thursday